[MUSIC] The Mini Vandals - In Memory of Jean Talon
4. Contract Theory
The right of property implies the right to make contracts about that property.
To give it away or exchange titles of ownership for the property of another person.
Unfortunately, many libertarians devoted the right to make contracts hold the contract
itself to be an absolute, and therefore maintain that any voluntary contract whatsoever must
be legally enforceable in the free society.
Marry Rothbard
As stated in the opening quote, property theory lies antecedent contract theory.
That is, the right to make contracts is implied by the right to own property, and not the other way around.
First, recall that property rights are conflict avoiding norms.
The owner is said to be a man who can justly control the resource in question,
but these ownership rights are not set in stone.
The owner of a property may abandon it or transfer title to someone else.
Consider Crusoe leaving his stick to rot after he's finished spearfishing.
If he no longer considers it to be a good which he's acting with,
Friday is capable of possessing it without there being any conflict.
In other words, owning anything involves actually possessing it,
along with the intent to direct the use of it.
If you lose this intent, you no longer own it.
This is abandonment, where a property is simply ceded back into nature,
ripe for someone else to homestead it.
Recall that such abandonment must be objective and inter-subjectively ascertainable.
The latter case of a man transferring title to someone else is the subject of the theory of contracts.
The question of concern is what types of contracts are enforceable and why.
Allow me to first construct the basic case of Crusoe transferring ownership of his stick to Friday.
For this to be a transfer and not an abandonment,
Crusoe must relinquish control at the same time that Friday takes up control
and each man must have the goal of the transfer going forth.
That is to say, there exists no time between Crusoe and Friday's ownership where the stick was unowned.
This means that a third man, Xury, could not come along and quickly swoop in on the property and thereby homestead it.
It's clear that Friday now has title to the property.
In short, a transfer of title to the stick from Crusoe to Friday
involves Crusoe abandoning the stick at the same time that Friday homesteads it.
What makes this transfer an enforceable contract is that if Crusoe does not
physically go through with giving up the stick, he has implicitly committed theft.
The stick belongs to Friday now and Crusoe is using it against Friday's consent.
This is because Crusoe's agreement to the contract is evidence
that he wishes to relinquish control, to abandon the stick,
he can't deny this without contradiction.
It is therefore those contracts where defaulting would imply aggression that are enforceable.
Consider a mere promise.
Say a woman agrees to marry her boyfriend but does not go through with it.
She has gone back on her word but she has not violated the boyfriend's consent.
Therefore, mere promises like this are not enforceable.
A promise is only enforceable to the extent they imply the transfer of property titles.
In such a case, the property may be repossessed by its now owner.
This theory of contract is called the title-transfer theory for this reason.
To sum up, only those contracts which define the terms of the transfer of title to alienable property are legitimate.
Furthermore, conditional transfers are also legitimate.
Say that Crusoe agrees to transfer title to the stick to Friday
on the condition that Friday performs a dance.
Upon Friday meeting the condition set forth by Crusoe, title to the stick is transferred to him.
This is because the intention made clear by both Crusoe and Friday
that Friday was the just director of the use of the stick upon the condition being met.
It will be seen in a later lesson why Crusoe would be "estopped" from challenging Friday's ownership.
That is to say, Crusoe could not coherently deny that Friday owns the stick
upon the condition being met.
A
What is important is that on this theory a contract is not a piece of paper.
The piece of paper is rather evidence of a contract existing.
The contract can be verbal, agreed to via semaphore,
or any matter of other methods of communication.
All that a piece of signed paper can do is serve as evidence
that a given contract was communicated and agreed upon by all the parties in question.
An interesting implication of this theory is that
there isn't really such a thing as breaching or breaking a contract.
If A and B agree that B will transfer to A a sum of 10 ounces of silver on the condition
that A performs magic at B's birthday party,
A has not violated B's rights by not showing up.
If B wanted to concourage A to go through with the deal,
he simply need bake in a penalty clause stating that
A transfers to B a sum of 5 ounces of silver if he does not perform the magic.
A
Still here, A does not breach the contract by not showing up.
He has simply engaged in an action which the contract covers.
The aggression would only be if A doesn't perform the magic and doesn't hand over the 5 ounces.
Not because this would breach the terms of the contract,
but because this would be a theft of 5 ounces of silver.
Consider further the case of Smith agreeing to pay 50 lbs of gold for Jones' car.
Smith takes the car but refuses to hand over the 50 lbs of gold to Jones.
Has Smith stolen the car or the 50 lbs of gold?
Well, if Smith actually has 50 lbs of gold,
then title to it was instantly transferred to Jones upon the contract being accepted.
Thus, it is the gold that has been stolen.
On the other hand, if Smith does not have 50 lbs of gold,
then the condition for the transfer of the car has not been met,
so Jones would still own the car and that is what Smith has stolen.
Fraud can be defined as theft by trick, i.e. is a theft performed by deceiving the victim.
Consider the example where Crusoe has blunted the tip of his spear
and that's why he wants to get rid of it.
Crusoe lies to Friday and claims that the spear is as sharp as a razor.
This is fraud.
Crusoe has deceived Friday about the nature of the spear.
This means that it was not a valid contract.
Crusoe did not have the intention of transferring title to a sharp spear to Friday
and therefore the contract is null.
A
If Friday had given Crusoe some seashells in exchange, Crusoe has implicitly stolen those shells.
A particularly prevalent example of fraud is found in fractional reserve banking.
The fractional reserve bank keeps only some fraction of the money deposited and loans out the rest.
Consider a full reserve bank.
Various people come and deposit 100 ounces of gold
and the bank therefore gives these depositors in total certificates for 100 ounces of gold.
Here there is a one-to-one correspondence between titles to gold,
evidenced by the certificates, and actual gold and the vault.
Consider what would happen if this bank decided to implement an 80% reserve policy
and they therefore loaned out 20 ounces of gold.
This would mean that the bank has stolen that gold
because there is already a one-to-one correspondence between property titles in the gold held by the depositors
and actual gold in the vault.
Therefore, the bank is committing a fraud in deceiving people into the belief that they actually hold title to that gold.
Perhaps instead of physically loaning out the gold,
they keep all of the gold they have, but they give out 20 ounces worth of certificates for gold.
This would still be fraud because there would be 120 ounces worth of titles to gold but only 100 ounces of gold.
A
More property titles and than actual property
implies that people being deceived about the nature of property in existence,
which therefore means there is fraud.
Often so called free banking exporters will hold that the right of the people to make
whatever contracts they expect to be advantageous means that such fractional reserve banks are not criminal institutions.
But as we have seen, these people are misunderstanding the nature of property and contracts.
It is not the case that one is able to make whatever contracts they want so long as everyone agrees to it.
Property theory lies antecedent to contract theory,
therefore a contract which misrepresents the actual nature of property and existence is invalid.
This is not to say that a fractional reserve casino game is fraudulent,
but representing this casino game as a bank is.
A bank is a money warehouse, not a casino game.
Such a casino game would not involve people deposting their money in their account
and retaining title as evidenced by money substitutes.
Such a game would involve people transferring their money to the casino
in order for the casino to engage in some gambling algorithm with it.
So fractional reserve banking is fraud, fractional reserve roulette is not.
The definition of fraud in terms of deception is another concept
that highlights the importance of communication to libertarian theory.
Just as me loaning my friend 5 ounces of silver
is not me deposting my money in account held by my friend,
is me transferring that silver to him.
So too is me placing a bet with a casino, not me disposing money in account,
is me transferring that bet to them.
This concept of a loan is relevant to the question of debtors prison.
The question is twofold, if A loans B 1000 ounces of silver in exchange for 1050 ounces of
silver in one year's time, but B defaults, has he stolen from A, and second, would A
be permitted to put B to work in a debtors prison to pay off the stolen sum?
For the former question, if it is the case that B has stolen from A, what has he stolen?
The 1000 ounces or the 1050 ounces?
He surely hasn't stolen the 1000 ounces
because that money was transferred to him at the time of the contract, such that he could invest in his various projects.
If it was not transferred, there would be no loan in the first place.
It also cannot be the case that it wasn't theft at the time,
but it is retroactively at the time when he defaults.
A property theory must assign a definite owner to any scarce resource at all times.
If retroactive theft is such a thing in your property theory,
there exists Schrödinger's property whose owner cannot be determined right here and now,
such that conflicts over its use may be avoided.
Schrödinger's property must therefore be expelled from our rational theory,
and as such, the notion of retroactive theft must also.
The question here is who owns the 1000 ounces immediately after the contract is accepted?
A or B?
If A then B has no right to invest these funds and there is no contract to speak of.
If B, then it cannot be that B has stolen 1000 ounces because he had title to it.
Furthermore, it also can't be said that B has stolen the 1050 ounces.
For if B has defaulted, that means that he does not possess 1050 ounces to silver.
So how could he possibly have stolen it if it doesn't exist?
Of course, if B actually does possess said sum of money and simply refuses to hand it over,
this is not strictly speaking a default on the loan, it is rather B stealing that sum of money.
These future-oriented contracts are called aleatory contracts.
They have an implied clause of "unless it's impossible."
This because the future is uncertain.
Just as you cannot contract a transfer title to a square circle,
you cannot contract a transfer money that doesn't exist.
So in such loan arrangements, there must be an implicit condition that the funds actually exist on the due date.
After all, what if B was vaporized in a nuclear explosion, along with the funds,
one week after the contract was accepted?
Upon the money coming due, has the now-dead B robbed A from beyond the grave?
What if everyone except A has died in that explosion?
If nobody else exists, it is nonsensical to speak of anyone being criminal towards A.
In short, it's not theft unless something was stolen, and it's not fraud unless there was deception.
A
There is no deception in the case of an aleatory contract on the part B,
as he's not deceiving A into thinking he has what he does not.
Everyone knows that the future is uncertain, B has made no claims to the contrary.
Whilst it's not relevant to legal theory as such how A can successfully get around this hurdle,
I think it is important to give some notion as to how future-oriented contracts are still possible and reasonable.
First, A need only bake in some interest clause.
Perhaps each month that passes B owes A a further 1% on top of the initial 1050 ounces,
such that when B acquires a requisite sum of money, title to it is immediately transferred to A.
Furthermore, it is not the job of law to make sure that A makes a profit on the loan.
Some loans go bad.
It is an entrepreneurial activity, and as such, it is per se uncertain.
The fact that the loan goes bad and A doesn't make a return
is not sufficient grounds to justify A locking up B in a prison and working him as a slave.
A
With our solid understanding of contract theory,
we can analyze the debate surrounding voluntary slavery and determine the correct answer.
The debate essentially centers around whether a man's self-ownership is alienable or not.
That is to say, the question is whether it's legitimate to transfer ownership of oneself to another person.
The former view is most notably held by Walter Block, and it can be summed up as follows:
A
The underlying point of the libertarian critique is that if I own something, I can sell it,
and should be allowed by a law to do so.
If I can't sell it, then, and to that extent, I don't really own it.
Taking my own liberty as perhaps the paradigm case of the debate over inalienability.
The claim is that if I really own my liberty, then I should be free to dispose of it as
I please.
Even if, by so doing, I end up no longer owning it.
Clearly, since I cannot own a square circle, I cannot sell it.
If I can own my ability to give true love, then I can sell it.
If, logically, I cannot own this attribute, then, of course, I can't give, barter or sell
it to anyone.
My thesis: no law should be enacted prohibiting or even limiting in any way people's rights
to alienate those things they own.
This is full-momenty alienability or commodification.
So for a voluntary slavery contract to be a legitimate, (1) you must own yourself in the first place,
and (2) you must be able to sell yourself.
Walter's contention with other libertarians is that there does not exist objects which are ownable but not sellable.
The standard example of a contract pertaining to the sale of a square circle is illegitimate
because you can't own a square circle in the first place.
This would imply that because people own themselves in the first place,
they can therefore sell themselves.
A prominent counter-argument to this thesis was forwarded by Rothbard in his Ethics of Liberty.
A
The distinction between a man's alienable labor service and his inalienable will may
be further explained.
A man can alienate his labor service, but he cannot sell the capitalized future value
of that service.
In short, he cannot, in nature, sell himself into slavery and have the sale enforced.
This would mean that his future will, over his own person, was being surrendered in
advance.
In short, a man can naturally expend his labor currently for someone else's benefit.
But he cannot transfer himself, even if he wished, into another man's permanent capital
good, for he cannot rid himself of his own will, which may change in future years and
repudiate the current arrangement.
The concept of voluntary slavery is indeed a contradictory one, for so long as a laborer
remains totally subservient to his master's will voluntarily, he's not yet to slave,
since his submission is voluntary.
Whereas if he later changes his mind and the master enforced his slavery by violence,
the slavery would not then be voluntary.
There are several ways a Blockean might respond to this attack.
Firstly, he could point the frontal lobotomy as a procedure which makes a person akin to
an animal in terms of thinking.
Perhaps there could be a pill or machine invented in the future which would nullify
only those parts of a man's brain, which were responsible for his conceptual faculties.
Surely a man who underwent a procedure such as these would have, indeed, potentially permanently,
subdued his will such that he may be more effectively directed by his enslaver.
This would mean that voluntary slavery is not per se illegitimate, but rather is only
illegitimate where men cannot figure out how to subdue the slave's will.
Furthermore, it's not the will which is relevant to the voluntary slavery contract, but the body.
So even if it is logically impossible to transfer the will of person A to person B,
it may not be the case that it's impossible to transfer the body from A to B.
After all, both the supporters and rejectors of the right to make slave contracts
agree that it is possible to have someone as your slave.
That is to say, it's possible for B to possess A.
The question is whether it's possible for this to be a just possession.
And on this note, let's recall the nature of a man's self-ownership.
A body is necessarily and objectively linked to an acting man.
It is this link which imbues a man with ownership.
Anytime you argue with anyone, you must assume the primacy of this link
and its validity in making the other person own their body.
It is the argument from argument then which demonstrates the inalienability of the self.
That is to say, ownership is just control, which means argumentatively justifiable control,
and the very nature of argumentatively justifying anything implies a mutual recognition of self-ownership.
Therefore, a master cannot justly possesses his slave, making voluntary slavery a contradiction in terms.
A
Block rejects this notion of an objective link establishing ownership, stating the following:
Let us posit that you have a dog who is heart and soul with you.
K9 dogs are said to have this sort of connection with their masters.
According to Kinsella, not only would it be illegal to sell this dog, but also well-nigh logically
impossible for this to occur.
Just as we all have the best link to my body, you too have the best link to this dog.
You snap your fingers and the dog does your bidding.
Not that of the neighbour.
To whom you have sold the dog.
The point is, the best link to in terms of control is clearly a way outside the bounds
of libertarian homesteading and property rights theory.
Merely because someone has the best link to something does not mean that he is a necessarily
legitimate owner of it.
But the dog is clearly disanalogous to the human case.
A dog is an external object, not a (human) body.
What we have in the case of a dog that A wants to sell to B,
is a case of either A or B "coercing" the dog to do their bidding.
The dog is analogous to a machine gun that A may well be more adept at using.
The point is not over who is more scientifically capable of using the object for some end though.
If the dog was capable of acting and arguing, then indeed it would be a contradiction to
assert that either A or B owned the dog, as they would have to recognize this dog's self-ownership.
This is because the dog would then have an objective and undeniable link to his own dog body.
A
The dog has no such link in reality because he cannot act or argue.
The dog is in the same legal category as a machine gun.
It may well be the case that A is more capable of using the dog for certain ends,
but this is not enough to demonstrate a link as strong
as it is between an actor-arguer and his own body.
Moreover, a first-principles understanding of contract highlights the fact that for
A to transfer title of alpha to B, A must relinquish control, i.e. abandon alpha,
at the same time that B takes up control.
You cannot abandon your body without making yourself brain dead, so you cannot,
whilst remaining an actor, transfer title to your body.
After all, such abandonment of the property would have to be objective and intersubjectively ascertainable.
Merely decreeing that you no longer own yourself is not enough.
What this means is that voluntary slavery is an impossibility.
Insofar as you do make yourself brain dead and thus non-existent in the praxeologic sense,
you cannot be said to consent or not consent to anything.
It is not proper to say that the stick I appropriate from nature is consenting or not consenting to be my slave.
A
It is a stick, not a moral being capable of consent.
Therefore, the closest that one can get to voluntary slavery
is to render the so-called slave, incapable of action or argumentation,
to completely destroy their will in Rothbardian terms,
and thus make this person legally analogous to a corpse.
Rothbard therefore already had the shape of this idea in his mind, but spoke of it using
the confusing terminology of will transfer.
As Block says, "will schmill!"
Whether you can literally transfer or suppress a will of an acting being isn't relevant.
What is relevant, however, and what Rothbard was on the cusp of is that consent does matter.
Merely promising in the present that you will do whatever your master says, that you will
be their slave, does not mean that they own you.
Mere promises do not establish this.
You can always change your mind in the future and revoke consent.
Consider the case of your girlfriend agreeing to have sex with you tomorrow after dinner.
The time comes and you are getting ready to do the deed, but she changes her mind and
tells you that she no longer wants to go forward with the arrangement.
But is she not my slave for the purposes of this contract?
She agreed before that she would obey my wishes on the matter.
So am I permitted to have sex with her, or would this be rape?
Clearly the latter is true, just because she gave her consent before,
does not imply that she cannot revoke this consent.
The same is true for all voluntary slavery.
Merely agreeing now to always obey the master's wishes does not transfer ownership of anything.
The Rothbardian analysis is also absolutely correct in that demolition of the will would
allow a body to be owned by another, but only because this demolition of will would render
the individual analogous to a corpse.
It is therefore not all that surprising that one cannot sell their body, whilst remaining alive.
After all, as discussed earlier, the two methods of alienation are title transfer and abandonment.
We already accept that it's not possible for an actor to abandon their body.
What the above analysis shows is that it's also not possible to alienate your body through title-transfer either.
Moreover, as discussed above, for title-transfer to be possible in the first place,
you have to be able to abandon the thing in question.
A
If A wants to transfer title of alpha to B,
what A must do is abandon title to alpha at the same time that B takes up title to alpha.
This first step of abandonment cannot occur in bodies,
and therefore ownership of bodies cannot be transferred.
The only exception is when the person in question dies or is rendered brain dead,
at this point their body is indeed abandoned in nature,
and as such the only valid way to transfer title to your own body is by doing so in a last will and testament.
It is a mistake to see property and external objects as being equivalent
to property in bodies, and then using the fact that you can
trade external objects to claim that you can also trade bodies.
Ownership is the right to control a scarce resource.
It takes an additional step to say that you can give up that right,
or that other people could take it in.
The confusion on this matter is derived from a conflation between two different senses of the word "ownership."
A
In this course, great attention has been paid to the legal sense of this word,
but there is also such a thing as catallactic ownership,
which is the sense used by economists.
This is why an economist might say something like A sells as labor services for five ounces of gold to B.
A
To the legal theorist such a sentence is incoherent.
The labor isn't owned by anyone, and thus isn't being traded.
It doesn't make sense to say that someone owns their labor,
labor is something that you do with things that you own.
After all, what would it mean to exclude someone from your labor?
Thus, in the legal sense, this is clearly ludicrous,
but the economist does not mean the same thing.
What the economist means by ownership is more akin to possession or control,
as the economist is not concerned with whether said control or possession is just.
A certainly does control his labor, at least in the economic sense.
He can choose to employ his labor for whatever line of production he sees fit.
And in the economic sense, it makes sense to speak of him trading this labor with other people.
A
But one should not then bring such an analysis into legal matters.
Such would be a dreadful mistake.
The voluntary slavery contract is the paramount example of this mistake.
Block's argument hinges on the notion that if you own something you can sell it, and vice versa.
A
But it is simply not the case that ownership implies selling, or that selling implies ownership.
I can sell a bitcoin, or an idea, or my labor,
and yet I do not own any of these things in the legal sense.
Similarly, owning something does not imply the right to sell it,
as has been seen in the case with the one's body.
It is possible to alienate some parts, or even all of your body, though.
Consider Crusoe chopping off his arm.
Upon chopping the arm off, it is alienable.
Crusoe is able to abandon, or trade it at will,
because he is no longer objectively and undeniably linked to his arm.
A similar case exists with respect to one's entire body, in the case of death.
If Crusoe sets to paper that, upon the condition that he dies,
ownership of his body is transferred to Friday, then this is a legitimate contract.
The instant the condition is met, Crusoe's body becomes alienable,
just as surely as a stick or seashell.
There could be no remaining objective link between Crusoe and his body
at this point, because Crusoe has perished.
He no longer possesses the potential to engage in any form of argumentation, and as such,
third parties are not in contradiction by claiming to own him.
This highlights why a last will and testament is a legitimate contract in general.
Simply set the condition for whatever title transfers the will defines,
to be the death of the owner.
Should a man die who has no inheritors, his property, including his body,
becomes instantly ceded to nature, ready for someone to homestead it.
Therefore, if a man wishes his corpse to be treated in a certain way,
he must transfer title to it to trusted family or a funeral home.