[MUSIC] The Mini Vandals - In Memory of Jean Talon
6. Defensive force and proportionality
No doubt punishment serves many purposes.
It can deter crime and prevent the offender from committing further crimes.
Punishment can even rehabilitate some criminals, if it is not capital.
It can serve to satisfy a victim's longing for revenge or his relatives' desire to avenge.
Punishment can also be used as a lever to gain restitution, recompense for some of the
damage caused by the crime.
For these reasons, the issue of punishment is and always has been of vital concern to
civilized people.
They want to know the effects of punishment and the effective ways of carrying it out.
Stephan Kinsella
Thusfar, this course has elucidated theories and examples denoting what is and what is not aggression.
Now that we know what it means to be criminal,
this lesson will answer the question of what actions are just in defending against and punishing aggressions.
A
First, what does it mean to punish?
Dictionary definitions are easy to come by, but in the sense that interests those of us
who want to punish, punishment is the infliction of physical force upon a person, in response
to something that he has done or failed to do.
Punishment thus comprises physical violence committed against a person's body, or against
any other property that a person legitimately owns, against any rights that a person has.
Punishment is for, or in response to some action, inaction or feature or status of the
person punished, otherwise it is simply random violence, which is not usually considered
to be punishment.
Thus when we punish a person is because we consider him to be a wrongdoer of some sort,
we typically want to teach him or others a lesson, or enact vengeance or restitution
for what he has done.
Note that the question of justifying a punishment only arises
insofar as the wrongdoer rejects the justice of the punishment.
That is to say, if the criminal consents to a certain retaliation, this retaliation is per se just,
as there can be no conflicts where the wills of men are in harmony.
Justifying a punishment is far more challenging when the criminal does not consent,
i.e., when the criminal wishes to challenge the justice of a given punishment.
We know from prior analysis that this challenge seeks to test the justification against the
nature of argumentally justifying as such.
If the punishment cannot be justified without thereby falling into contradiction, it is unjust.
Therefore, the nature of argumentation is a suitable starting point to obtain a rational
theory of punishment, recall that contradictions are falsehoods,
and thus not a feature of a correct argument.
Therefore, a person can be prevented from making certain claims in a dialectic
if those claims are inconsistent with his actions.
To be abundantly clear, to avoid any confusion, the person is not being prevented from making
these claims by a judge or a cop or whatever, physically coercing him into not making claims.
He's prevented from making these claims by the very nature of dialectic as such.
In other words, if he did make those knowingly incorrect claims,
he would not be engaged in argumentation, he would rather be babbling or telling a joke or something else.
This forms the root of what Kinsella dubs "Dialogical Estoppel."
Lord Coke explains that the word estoppel is used because a man's own act or acceptance
stoppeth or closeth up his mouth, and dialogical refers to dialogue, aka argumentation,
so we can say that a man is, by the nature of argumentation as such,
estopped from making certain inconsistent or contradictory claims.
QUOTE To say that a person is estopped from making certain claims means that these claims cannot
even possibly be right, because they are contradictory, is to recognise that his assertion is simply
wrong because it is contradictory.
Applying estoppel in such a manner perfectly complements the very purpose of dialogue.
Dialogue is by its nature an activity aimed at finding truth.
Anyone engaging in argument is necessarily endeavouring to discern the truth about some
particular subject, to the extent that this is not the case, there is no dialogue occurring,
but mere babbling or even physical fighting, nor can this be denied.
Anyone engaging in an argument long enough to deny that truth is the goal of the discourse
contradicts himself, because he is himself asserting or challenging the truth of a given
proposition.
Thus the assertion as true of anything that simply cannot be true is incompatible with
the very purpose of discourse, anything that cannot be true is contrary to the truth finding
END QUOTE purpose of discourse, and thus is not permissible within the bounds of a discourse.
Let us apply this theory of estoppel to the case of A punching B.
Assume that this is the extent of the assault, as the question of defending against
an ongoing aggression shall be discussed in the next section.
B decides that he wants to punish A in an eye-for-an-eye manner by punching him back,
or perhaps by hiring a champion C to punch A if B cannot or does not want to do this himself.
If A were to challenge this punishment he would claim that this punching of him
is an impermissible action, i.e. that people should be prohibited from punching him,
but A has previously demonstrated that he thinks he should not be prohibited from punching B.
A has presupposed that punching people sans-consent is just,
and is now explicitly making claim that it is unjust.
This is a clearly incoherent position.
Thus A is estopped from challenging his punishment, therefore we revert back to the simple case
of an unchallenged punishment, which is per se just.
Note that this applies only to punching as the punishment.
A could coherently argue that it is unjust to murder him, or to take a lock of his hair,
or to tear up his prized roses, as these retaliations would be of an entirely different sort.
A
That is, by merely punching B, A presupposes only that punching is proper conduct,
but he does not per se presuppose that any other invasions of property borders are proper.
This is where the concept of proportionality comes in.
The retribution against an aggressor must come in the same form as the aggression,
or else the punishment is further aggression, and thus not just.
In short, just retribution is an eye for an eye, not an eye for a tooth.
There are a number of potential objections to this theory that A might forward.
First he might claim that his positions are not that punching is proper, and that punching is improper,
but rather that A punching B is proper, and anyone punching A is improper.
Thus there is no contradiction, and he is not estopped from challenging his punishment.
The issue here is that any norm must in principle be universalisable,
if it is to be proposed in an argument, as Hoppe points out.
Quite commonly, it has been observed that argumentation implies that a proposition claims universal
acceptability, or should it be a norm proposal that is universalizable.
Applied to norm proposals, this is the idea, as formulated by the Golden Rule of Ethics
or the Kantian Categorical Imperative, that only those norms can be justified, that
END QUOTE can be formulated as general principles, which are valid for everyone without exception.
This is because, if one is to claim any proposition as being argumentatively valid,
said proposition must be rational.
What this means is that it must in principle be valid, no matter who it is proposed to.
To reject this would be to adopt a polylogism, i.e. that a proposition might be true when
levied in one argument, but not when levied in another, and it was shown in the first lesson
that polylogism implies contradiction, making it false.
So universalisability is therefore a pre-supposition of the very normative discourse that A would
be partaking in by attempting to reject his punishment, but the norm that it is fine for
A to punch B, but not for others to punch A, is not universalisable.
We would be faced with a contradiction if we tried to swap out A for B and hold both
norms simultaneously, meaning this norm cannot be applied to everyone.
QUOTE escape the application of the estoppel by arbitrarily specialising his otherwise inconsistent
END QUOTE views with liberally sprinkled "for me only's."
Kinsella points out further that even if we were to throw away the requirement of universalisability,
and instead assume that norms can be particularised in this way, this would mean that B could
simply particularise his punishment norm, and thus claim it to be just for him to retaliate.
We would quickly regress into incoherent subjectivist ramblings of might making right,
so this objection by particularisation fails, leaving our aggressor estopped once more.
A second potential counter A might raise, however, is that he has changed his mind,
i.e. he used to think it proper to punch people, but he has had a change of heart
and now realises that such conduct is evil, and therefore he is not currently in contradiction,
and thus not estopped from objecting to his punishment.
There are a number of problems with A's approach here.
First, if changing one's mind means that one is no longer liable for prior actions,
then all B must do is punch A, then afterwards claim that he has changed his mind about that
punishment, meaning he is also not responsible. You'll notice that this would quickly devolve
into might-plus-regret and makes right, which would be an irrational ethic.
Second, by A changing his mind, he is per se denouncing his prior actions, thus asserting
that aggressions are indeed impermissible. This would mean that he could not coherently deny
the right of the victim of aggression to punish their aggression. To say that an action is
permissible is to say that one may not legally punish it.
Third, this mind-changing is still a form of particularisation, it is to claim that the
logical structure of what it means to presuppose an action as a legitimate can change by the
mere fact that the person presupposing said legitimacy also thinks that the action
is illegitimate. Let's unpack this. What A is asserting here is that they believe in
their heart that punching is illegitimate, whether they only start holding this fact
after doing the punching isn't particularly relevant. All that matters is that at the
moment of the assault, A must presuppose that punching is a legitimate action. This could
take place simultaneously with A believing it to be illegitimate or not, men are capable
of believing in contradictory things after all. What is important is that A cannot drop
the presupposition that punching is illegitimate. He has already committed the act of aggression
that presupposes this as a legitimate interaction. Because he cannot drop the presupposition,
in order to resolve the contradiction, he is left with only the option of dropping his
challenge to aggression. Therefore, he is estopped by definition.
I will reiterate this point for clarity. What makes a man estopped from challenging a given
punishment is that the given challenge would imply a contradiction, meaning that it cannot
be uttered in an argument. When I perform some action X, I thereby presuppose by this performance
that I think I should do X as opposed to not X. There is some confusion over this thesis.
Often, I have encountered the counter-argument of the man who is smoking and says that he should stop.
Does this man not believe that he should stop? Is he lying when he says he should stop?
That is not necessarily the case. We can indeed imagine a man who is currently
engaged in the act of smoking. A man who is chosen to smoke rather than not smoke, who
nonetheless believes that he should not smoke. This does not establish that he is not also
presupposing that he should smoke. It is possible for a person to hold two contradictory beliefs
at the same time. We call this cognitive dissonance. Consider the anarchist who goes through
the labor of demonstrating that taxation is theft and that theft is bad. Therefore,
taxation is bad, only to be confronted by a statist opponent who agrees that taxation
is theft and that is bad, but still asserts that taxation is a good thing that should continue.
It is clear to anyone who has encountered stupid people that a man is fully capable
of holding contradictory theses at the same time. The upshot of this for our smoker is
that by choosing to smoke rather than not smoke, it must be the case that he believes
that he should smoke rather than not smoke. But this does not preclude the possibility
that our smoker also believes that he should not smoke. It is just that his belief that
he should smoke is in some way overpowering his contradictory belief. There is a further
confusion to be addressed at this point, which stems from a conflation between two
different senses of the word "ought." To highlight this, consider the statement, it is raining
outside. Therefore, you ought bring an umbrella. Now, there are two ways which one
could interpret this statement. Either (1) ought is being used in its precise logical
meaning, or (2) it is being used as prudential advice. For (1) it simply does not follow
that because it is raining, you ought bring an umbrella, at least not without additional steps.
For (2) ought is being used colloquially. If we were to precisely formulate (2) it
would be something like, it is raining outside, so if you do not wish to get wet when you go
outside, a potential means to achieve this goal would be to bring an umbrella. When formulated
precisely, it becomes clear that when prudential advice is given like this, the statement is
really an is statement, rather than an ought statement. This insight will become crucial
in the next lesson, so I will not stress it too heavily here. But the key takeaway for
now is that there is only ought. Ought is ought. There doesn't exist different "flavours"
of ought in logic. It is a failure of imprecision to mix and colloquial usages of this word.
Bringing this back to our criminal A, who wishes to challenge his punishment for punching
B, he has already demonstrated by his conduct that he thinks punching is a legitimate interaction
if he then states that it is not a legitimate interaction, which is required for him to
challenge this punishment, he is in contradiction. To resolve a contradiction between these two
statements, one of the statements has to be dropped. Because they simply cannot drop
the statement that punching is proper, he is left only with being able to drop the statement
that punching is improper. The statement that punching is improper is the one that is required
for him to challenge the punishment. Therefore, A cannot challenge his punishment. He is dialogically estopped from doing so.
An important note must be made with respect to the application of this theory of dialogical estoppel.
A keen eye will notice that men are only estopped insofar as they chose to commit the aggression.
That is, a man is only estopped when he purposefully engaged in the trespass in question.
If a man did not purposefully aggress but rather accidentally aggressed,
we say that he lacks mens rea. Mens rea is a legal term meaning guilty mind.
It is characteristic of the man who decides that he wants to aggressively
stab his neighbour to death, but not for the man who is hiking and accidentally wanders
on to a farmer's field. mens rea is contrasted with actus reus, meaning guilty act.
Actus reus is present in every man who trespasses, whether they did so knowingly or not.
Restitution can be justified on the grounds of actus reus. Retribution requires mens rea.
Here, restitution refers to the act of making a victim whole again. Say I steal 5 ounces of silver
from my neighbour. Restitution would involve me giving my neighbour 5 ounces of silver.
Retribution would involve a further 5 ounces of silver. In total, assuming I knowingly stole, my neighbour
would be due 10 ounces of silver, 5 in restitution and 5 in retribution.
As a point of clarification, mens rea does not require that the person in question actually understands
that their action was criminal. All that is required is that they knowingly perform the invasion.
For instance, the Nazi prison guard who shoots an escaping Jew has knowingly invaded that
Jew's body with his bullet. However, that guard may well believe that his action was
justifiable because he believed in German law, rather the natural law, but his belief
that the action was just does not absolve him, as he knowingly performed that which is objectively an invasion.
With an objective theory of the just means of punishment elucidated,
we shall move on to an analysis of what means of defence are just. Recall that a property
right in X, held by a person A, implies the right of A to exclude other people from the use of X.
It is from this recognition that defence is justified, namely, A is permitted
to use whatever means are required to go about excluding people from X. This simple principle
is, however, not so simple to actually apply to complex scenarios. First, consider the
case of a man trespassing onto your front lawn to take a look at your roses.
It is clear that insofar as you do not wish for him to be there, there is trespassing occurring,
that is he cannot use your lawn to stand on at the same time that you wish for him to
not stand on your lawn. Therefore, you may exclude the man from doing so, but could you
do so through arbitrary means? For instance, would you be permitted to fire a rocket at
his feet, thereby blowing him up, or would you have to take "gentler" means first?
Let's consider the relevant rights. The man owns his body and therefore has a right to exclude
you from his body, but you own your lawn, and thus can exclude him from using your lawn.
Therefore you are permitted to possess him to the extent that it is required to remove
him from your lawn and no more. For instance, perhaps the man did not realise
it was your property, but rather a natural feature that is not owned by anyone.
Here, the man would lack mens rea, and perhaps simply informing him that he is trespassing
will suffice to remove him from your lawn. Here, no possession of his body would be required,
and thus no possession could be justified. However, the man might be stubborn and wish
to look at your roses still. This more stubborn man may require that you grab him by the arm
and walk him off your property. Here, because the grabbing of the arm was required to remove
him, it can be justified. You could not grab his arm and begin stabbing at him with a needle,
as the stabbing with a needle does not serve the purpose of excluding the land from your
property, and is not required for this exclusion. Therefore, this stabbing would be an additional
aggressive invasion of the man, rather than of your lawn. Here, it becomes clear that
you would not be permitted to launch a rocket at the man, unless said launching of a rocket
was required to successfully exclude him. A further example to elaborate upon this principle
is your neighbour kicking his ball onto your lawn. Let's imagine first that your neighbour
doesn't want anyone else to touch his ball, and you don't know what's for the ball
to be on your lawn. Here, the ball is invading your property, so you could justly remove
the ball at will, i.e. you're allowed to exclude the ball from your property, and touching
the ball is required to remove it. Imagine an alternative scenario where the ball is
on your property, and to teach him a lesson, you tell your neighbour that you will not
let him retrieve the ball himself, and you will not remove the ball from your property on your own.
This would be a case of excluding the neighbour from his ball, which you're not
trying to exclude from your property. Because you aren't trying to exclude the ball from
your property, it could not be said that the ball has invaded your property. The neighbour
still owns the ball, and therefore you're engaging an act of forestalling. You're excluding
your neighbour from the ball that you do not own. However, if you did attempt to exclude
the ball from your property, perhaps by erecting a fence, and your neighbour was nonetheless
able to overcome your exclusion, the ball is invading your property.
Perhaps this fence completely encloses your property, such that for the neighbor to retrieve his ball
the fence would have to be removed. Certainly, you'd be permitted here to continue to exclude
your neighbour from stepping on to retrieve his ball, as his stepping on to your property
would involve a further invasion, because you're already excluding people from your property
prior to the ball being kicked on. Here the principle is that antecedent rights must prevail.
You're excluding people and balls from your lawn, which is why you own your wall.
You cannot be compelled to allow further invasions to recover from the cost of prior invasions.
Your neighbour must suck it up and hope that you decide to return his ball to him.
This is because your rights to the lawn are antecedent to your neighbour's rights in the ball,
as the ball is used to initiate the conflict. You are rightly allowed to take possession
of his invading ball. Dominiak's contradiction from donut homesteads is resolved here by
your possession of that ball being just. You gain ownership of that ball by virtue of it
being invasive. This is not full-monte ownership, however, like in the case of owning
a stick where you can trade it or use it however you wish, this ownership of the ball would be
specifically for the purpose of excluding invaders from retrieving the ball. If you removed the ball
from your property, it would revert back to the ownership of your neighbour. This analysis applies
also to the cases where a bird drops the ball onto your property, or where a third party kicks the ball,
but not where you kick your neighbour's ball onto your property, as you initiated the conflict
there. The insight that even where your neighbour was not responsible for the invasion of the ball,
you may still take possession of it is key for understanding the libertarian answer to the human
body shield. Consider the case where a criminal steals your neighbour's sword and attempts to
stab you with it, and the only way to prevent this from happening is by damaging the sword.
Because damaging the sword is required in excluding the invasion, it is just, even if your neighbour
does not want the sword to be damaged. Similarly, if the criminal instead picks your neighbour up and
tries to use him as a sword, you'd be justified in damaging your neighbour's body in so far as
this is required to exclude the criminal's invasions.
QUOTE instead of attacking you with stolen property, the criminal instead shields himself with stolen
property. For example, say the criminal wraps himself and your neighbour's quilt, approaches
you and then begins shooting at you. As you take cover and draw your side arm, your neighbour yells,
END QUOTE don't shoot my quilt, as a libertarian must you respect the preference of your neighbour,
In such a scenario, you'd be justified in taking whatever actions are required
to exclude the criminal's attempted invasion as always.
It is required that you shoot back in order to thwart him. Thus, this is just.
Even though it would imply damaging your neighbour's quilt, moreover, your neighbour would not be
justified in attacking you to defend his quilt. You are doing no wrong by shooting through the quilt.
Therefore, your neighbour cannot justify attacking you, as he is not responding to an aggression on
your part. We can then trivially move from the criminal using a quilt shield to one using your
neighbour as a shield. Again, you are justified in shooting back at the criminal,
even if this implies shooting through your neighbour.
QUOTE had connected to device to your neighbour that would kill him if the criminal were to die.
If you defend yourself against the criminal, then your neighbour will suffer. Yet, as in the previous
case, your rights are antecedent to those of your neighbour. The aggressor brought his property into
conflict. The violation of your neighbour's property rights occurs when the criminal connects
the device to him, and when the criminal attacks you, not when you killed the criminal. Furthermore,
END QUOTE your neighbour would not be justified in attacking you to try and prevent you from killing the criminal.
This is distinct from the situation where your neighbour is a bystander to the aggression.
In such a situation, attacking him is not required to exclude the aggressive
invasions from the criminal, so randomly turning around and shooting at him during the gunfight
would be an additional aggression insofar as this is not required to thwart the bad guy.
The same is true if you are given an ultimatum by the criminal, where he will shoot you if you
do not kill your neighbour. You are allowed only to engage in exclusionary actions against the aggressor,
not against bystanders. These exclusionary actions may well damage the property of third parties,
this is not provide carte blanche for whatever invasions you may wish to engage in, to exclude,
to clarify exclusion is only justified against aggressors. However, exclusion against aggressor
may or may not involve damage to the property of third parties. This damage can only be
justified if it is required to exclude the aggressor.