7. An elaboration on the nature of law as a subset of ethics
Value is objective, not intrinsic or subjective. Value is based on and derives from the facts
of reality. It is not derived from mystic authority or from whim, personal or social.
Reality we hold, along with the decision to remain in it, i.e. to stay alive, dictates and demands
the entire code of values. Unlike the lower species, man does not pursue the proper values
automatically. He must discover and choose them, but this does not imply subjectivism.
Every proper value judgement is the identification of a fact. A given object or action advances
man's life. It is good, or it threatens man's life. It is bad, or an evil. The good, therefore,
is a species of the true. It is a form of recognising reality. The evil is a species of the false.
It is a form of contradicting reality. Or, values are a type of fact. They are facts
considered in relation to the choice to live. Existentially, an action of man is good or bad
according to its effect. Its effect is positive or negative on man's life. Thus, creating a
skyscraper is good, and murdering the architect is bad, both by the standard of life. A human
action is not merely physical motion. It is a product of man's ideas and value judgments,
true or false, which themselves drive from a certain kind of mental cause,
ultimately from thought or from evasion. The skyscraper's creator, function on the basis
of proper value judgments and true ideas, including a complex, specialised knowledge.
So you must have expended mental effort, focus, work. So one praises him morally
and admires him. But the murderer acted on ideas of value judgments that defy reality.
So you must have evaded and practised whim worship. So one condemns him morally and despises him.
Leonard Peikoff
In the preparation for and the writing of this course, I have encountered a strange tendency,
wherein the claim that people ought not violate the rights of others is apparently a controversial
one, even among Austrians. This is indicative of a severe problem in Austro-libertarian
circles that deserves a dedicated section of this course to properly address.
The root for this problem is that many reject the core definition of law as a subset of ethics,
claiming instead that there is such a thing as a virtuous crime. The paragon example would be a
man who is about to commit suicide by jumping off of a cliff. And the only way to save this man
is to violate his rights by grabbing him and dragging him away from the cliff's edge.
These contextualist-libertarians would have it that whether a crime is moral or not depends on
extra-legal context. I believe much of the confusion on this topic stems from the fact that many
libertarians at least appear to be somewhat inconsistent. At some points indicating that law
is indeed a subset of ethics and at other points rejecting this position. Rothbard explicitly
states his work on pollution, that law is a subset of ethics and a set of ought or normative
propositions. But his discussion of lifeboat scenarios in The Ethics of Liberty, is commonly
cited to negate this point. Rothbard presents the conundrum as follows:
QUOTE that the existence of extreme or lifeboat situations disproves any theory of absolute property rights,
or indeed of any absolute rights of self-ownership whatsoever. It is claimed that since any theory
of individual rights seems to break down or works unsatisfactorily in such fortunately rare
situations, therefore there can be no concept of inviolable rights at all. In a typical lifeboat
situation there are, let us say, eight places in a lifeboat putting out from a sinking ship,
END QUOTE and there are more than eight people wishing to be saved. Who then is to decide who should
On its face, this appears to not present any serious problem to
the theory presented in this course. The fact that the truth of the matter is unsatisfactory
or makes someone upset or look like a bad guy for presenting it does not constitute a refutation
of said truth. Indeed, to warp one's ethics to suit one's intuition such that any "unsatisfactory"
results are purged would be to surrender oneself to accepting the mystic power of whim to grant
truth, thus tainting an otherwise sound epistemology, thus I shall proceed with the analysis without
caring about how nasty-sounding the conclusion reached may be. In the first place we have a scarcity,
only eight spots in a lifeboat and more than eight people, thus property rights must be assigned.
Presumably this lifeboat did not materialise in nature and was instead built by or purchased
by whomever owns the boat, thus it is he who gets the right to say who gets a spot, perhaps he makes
a rule that women and children go first, perhaps he decides that crewmates get priority over customers
and so on. Whatever arbitrary rules he sets ought be abided. Now what of the situation where the
owner set no rules forth and has died abandoning lifeboat to the domain of nature? We surely
have our solution in the homesteading principle. First come, first served. If you get to a spot in the
lifeboat you're thus using said spot and thus get to dictate how it is to be used. Presumably
you want it to be used to save yourself. This might be horribly unfair to those who are slower or
started further away from the lifeboat, but tough luck! Life isn't fair and neither is law.
The prime goal of law is justice, not fairness. What, after all, would be the alternative? That
people who are slower to get to the boat, i.e. late comers are the ones who should get a spot?
Well, then the people they kick out could just immediately return to the boat as an even later
comer, thus entering us into an endless dance of groups getting in and out of the boat.
Everyone would be equal, but everyone would be dead. It seems that Rothbard came to the same conclusion:
QUOTE If the owner of the boat, or his representative, e.g. the captain of the ship,
has died in the wreck, and if he has not laid down no rules in advance of the wreck for allocation
of seats in such a crisis, then the lifeboat may be considered at least temporarily for the
emergency, abandoned, and therefore unowned. At this point, our rules for unowned property
come into play, namely that unowned resources become the property of the first people possessing
them. In short, the first eight people to reach the boat are, in our theory, the proper owners
and users of the boat. Anyone who throws them out of the boat then commits an act of aggression
in violating the property right of the homesteader he throws out of the boat. After he returns to
shore, then the aggressive becomes liable for prosecution for his act of violation of property
right, as well, perhaps for the murder of the person he rejected out of the boat.
Rothbard continues with the following. In the first place, a lifeboat situation is hardly a
valid test of a theory of rights, or any moral theory whatsoever. Problems of moral theory
in such an extreme situation do not invalidate a theory in normal situations. In any sphere of
moral theory, we are trying to affirm an ethic for man, based on his nature and the nature of the
world, and this precisely means for normal nature, for the way life usually is, and not for rare or
abnormal situations, is a wise maxim of law for precisely this reason that hard cases make bad
law. We are trying to frame an ethic for the way men generally live in the world. We are not,
after all, interested in framing an ethic that focuses on situations that are rare, extreme,
and not generally encountered. Let's take an example to illustrate their point.
Outside the sphere of property rights, or rights in general, and within the sphere of ordinary
ethical values. Most people would concede the principle that it is ethical for a parent to save
his child from drowning, but then our lifeboat skeptic could arise, and our all is challenged.
Aha, but suppose that two of your children are drowning, and you can only save one. Which
child would you choose? And doesn't the fact that you'd have to let one child die and they get the
very moral principle that you should save your drowning child? I doubt whether many ethicists
would throw over the moral desirability or principle of saving one's child because it
END QUOTEcould not be fully applied in such a lifeboat situation. Yet why should the lifeboat case be
The response here indicates that there are at least two different spheres of ethics.
One for normal situations, and one for abnormal ones. It is not clear, however,
how on earth it could be possible to make a non-arbitrary distinction between normal and
abnormal ethical conundrums. Moreover, as such a principled distinction cannot be made between
normal and abnormal such a theory be particularistic and thus irrational. That is to say, there are
certainly many differences that one could use to define normal as opposed to abnormal. Say that
situations where red shirts are worn are abnormal, and the ones where red shirts are not worn,
the situation is normal. That would be a difference, but the difference is not relevant to ethical
theory. Thus a rational norm must apply to both classes of situations in order to be universal,
as opposed to particular. Until such a principled difference can be found to define normal as
opposed to abnormal, we are stuck with universal norms having to apply to both classes, and thus
there are not two "spheres" of moral theory. That is to say, it couldn't be the case that
property rights hold normally, but not abnormally. Such would be a particularistic property norm,
and thus an irrational one. I must now consider Rothbard's drowning children hypothetical.
In the case of a single child, it is assumed that parent can save them, and in the case of
two children it is assumed that only one can be saved. There are indeed certain similarities
between the drowning children and Lifeboat, so the case of two children, one will die, and one will
live. For the Lifeboat, eight will live, and others will die. The question is how to determine
who should live and who should die. We have our solution in the case of the Lifeboat,
and it strikes me that this course provides a similar ability to answer the drowning children
hypothetical. The mother cannot physically save both, and thus it is surely a matter of personal
preference which one she saves. And why should she be expected to act any differently? It would
be logically impossible for her to pick the one that she would prefer not to save, and thus the
only alternative would be to let both drown. Surely we can easily sum this up in a universal
principle. Guardians ought save their children from drowning insofar as they have the ability
to. It is not my claim that this principle has been proven, after all this is a law course,
not a course on ethics in general, but I can't see how this would not be universal,
and it certainly seems that it easily deals with Rothbard's hypothetical opponent.
Rothbard seemingly goes forth with his multi-sphere model:
to our theory as follows. That theory of property rights, or even of self-ownership,
is driveable from the conditions by which man survives and flourishes in this world,
and that therefore, in this kind of extreme situation, or mass faced with the choice of either
saving himself or violating the property rights of the Lifeboat owner, or in the above example of
the homesteader of the boat, and it is ridiculous to expect him to surrender his life on behalf
of the abstract principle of property rights. Because of this kind of consideration, many
libertarians who otherwise believe in property rights gravely weaken them on behalf of the
contextualist contention that, given a choice between his life and a grazing against someone
else's property or even life, it is moral for him to commit the aggression, and that therefore,
in such a situation, these property rights cease to exist. The error here on the part of
the contentious libertarian is to confuse the question of the moral course of action for the
person in such a tragic situation, with a totally separate question of whether or not his seizing
of Lifeboat or Planck Space by force constitutes an invasion of someone else's property right,
for we are not in constructing a theory of liberty and property, i.e. a political ethic,
concerned with all personal moral principles. We are not here with concern whether it is moral
or immoral for someone to lie, to be a good person, to develop his faculties, or be kind or mean to
his neighbours. We are concerned in this sort of discussion solely with such political ethical
questions as the proper rule of violence, the sphere of rights, or the definitions of criminality
and aggression. Whether or not it is moral or immoral for Smith, the fellow excluded by the
owner from the Planck or the Lifeboat, to force someone else out of the Lifeboat or whether he
END QUOTE should die heroically instead, is not our concern and not the proper concern of a theory of political
On a first glance, it would seem that Rothbard is adopting a dichotomy between law and ethics,
and this passage would mean sighted to me numerous times to that effect. But to my eye, this is only
one of multiple valid interpretations of Rothbard's writing here. It appears to me that he is merely
hedging his bets and ignoring the questions of ethics as a whole and focusing in on the area
that he has expertise in. This highlights why Rothbard saw fit to analyse the Lifeboat scenario
to "ordinary ethical values;" if law was not a subset of ethics, i.e. if it did not deal with
ought statements, such an analogy would be incoherent. Furthermore, Rothbard is correct here that we
are not, in constructing a theory of liberty and property, concerned with all personal moral
principles. We are rather only concerned with those moral principles that pertain to conflicts
over scarce means. This does not, as the critics claim, demonstrate that law and ethics are disconnected
fields. Clearly, if we are concerned with a subset of all moral principles which deals specifically
with conflicts in doing law, then law itself is a subset of morality in general. This analysis is
also consistent with Rothbard's claim that whether or not it is moral or immoral for Smith,
the fellow excluded by the owner from the plank or the Lifeboat, to force someone else out of the
Lifeboat, or whether he should die heroically instead, is not our concern and not the proper
concern of a theory of political ethics. It very much appears to me that Rothbard is merely leaving
the floor open for his legal theory to be compatible with any outside ethical theory that one may come
up with, even one which would allow for contradictions between "personal" and "political" ethics. Of course,
such a theory would be false, but that is not the concern of Rothbard qua legal theorist.
This becomes clear in a footnote attached to the end of the above paragraph, commenting on an example
where two men are floating in the water and there's a plank that can save only one of them:
QUOTE Eric Mack's example fails to show a necessary conflict between property rights and moral
principles. The conflict in his example is between property rights and the dictates of prudence
or self-interest, but the latter is only dominated morality if one adopts moral equalism,
END QUOTE which indeed Professor Mack does, but which is only one possible moral theory.
This makes it abundantly clear to me that Rothbard is, as I claim, simply trying to make his ethic as narrow
as possible such that it may be slotted into any general ethical theory.
QUOTE The crucial point is that even if the contextualist libertarians may say that,
given the tragic context, Smith should throw someone else out of the lifeboat to save his own life,
he is still committing, at the very least, invasion of property rights, and probably also
murder of the person thrown out, so that even if one says that he should try and save his life
by forcibly grabbing a seat in the lifeboat, he is still, in our view, liable to prosecution as
a criminal invader of property right, and perhaps as a murderer as well. After he's convicted,
it would be the right of the lifeboat owner or the heir of the person tossed out to forgive Smith,
to pardon him because of the unusual circumstances, but it would also be the right not to pardon
and to proceed with the full force of their legal right to punish. Once again, we are concerned in
this theory with the rights of the case, not, with whether or not a person chooses to voluntarily
exercise his rights. In our view, the property owner or the heir of the killed would have the
right to prosecute and to exact proper punishment upon the aggressor. The fallacy of the contextualists
is to confuse considerations of individual personal morality, what should Smith do,
END QUOTE with the question of the rights of the case. The right to property continues, then, to be absolute,
Again, Rothbard's use of the even if disclaimer prior to the hypothetical proof
that Smith should throw someone out of the lifeboat is a crystal-clear
signal that Rothbard is merely entertaining this as a hypothetical counter to his thesis.
What Rothbard has done is that he is shown his theory of property rights to hold, even if
someone were to prove that there are separate personal and political spheres of ethics.
To reiterate, Rothbard has not here accepted that there is indeed such a proof, all he has done
is shown that the existence of such a proof is irrelevant to his legal theory. Of course,
such a proof does not exist, as said multi-sphere ethics would be a polylogism.
Ought is ought, there is not ought-but-personal, and a separate ought-but-political, there is only ought.
Confusion on this matter comes down to colloquial usage of the word ought. In sentences like,
you ought wear a coat because you don't want to get wet. There are two ways we can interpret
this statement. Either we assume that ought is being used in its precise logical meaning,
or we assume it is being used as prudential advice. In the former case, the statement is
simply invalid. It does not follow from the fact that a person doesn't want to get wet,
that they ought prevent themselves from getting wet by wearing a coat. After all,
I may want to rape a baby, but it does not follow from the existence of this whim that I actually
ought obey it. The latter interpretation of ought being a prudential advice is a colloquial
usage of the word. What is really being said is, if you do not want to get wet, wearing a coat
will achieve this goal, which is clearly an is statement. All that is being said is that the
given strategy will attain the goal, not whether the goal is proper. Thus, it could not be that
politically you ought not aggress but personally you ought aggress, as that would be a contradiction.
You ought aggress, and you ought not aggress. Then it appears to me that Rothbard holds law
as a subset of ethics, but has also successfully shielded his theory from any attack which would
seek to separate them. This stance becomes confusing in the light of modern Austrian theorists.
Hoppe has shown with his argumentation ethics that any attempt at negating the NAP leads to contradiction,
but elsewhere claims that he was not attempting to drive an ought from an is, but surely if an
ought statement which negates the NAP falls into contradiction, its negation must be true? This
will be analysed in greater depth below, but for now the contextualist counter-thesis to my
position is summed up explicitly by Konrad Graf:
QUOTE praxeology enables its reconstruction as a categorical and definitional assessment of what
types of actions are NAP infringements, separate from moral assessment of such infringements.
In this view, an example of an ethical statement would be one or not violate rights. Legal theory
END QUOTEhelps us to make this go actionable by supplying information concerning the question, what is
And what, then, does it mean to violate a right? As I'm sure Konrad would agree,
it means that you could not justify your conduct, but what does it mean that you cannot justify
your conduct? It means that you cannot claim that your conduct should go forth, as said claim
implies a contradiction. Thus, its negation that your conduct should not go forth is true.
This is a legal claim and an ethical one. In fact, every legal claim is also an ethical claim,
as every legal claim is a claim about which party should have possession in the conflict at hand.
QUOTE There is an intuitive relationship between law and ethics. However, I argue that it is not one
of a field to a subfield, but rather of an advisor relationship between two distinct fields.
If one takes on the moral objective of not agressing, one is more likely to be successful at this in
action, with a clear idea of what aggression is. Rights and statements become one category of
wrongs next to other non-legal categories of wrongs that a given ethical system may specify.
Yet the definition of what constitutes infringing rights is derived independently of ethics using
the categorical, counterfactual method of praxeology. Although argumentation ethics establishes that
END QUOTE no propositional argument against the NAP can succeed, it does not prevent human beings from
Indeed, Konrad is correct that argumentation ethics does not
prevent people from engaging in aggression, but it does demonstrate that any attempted
justification of that aggression would fall into contradiction. That is to say, any claim that
one ought agress implies a contradiction, thus its negation that one ought not agress is true,
just as the fact that one plus one makes two does not prevent people from acting erroneously
on the thought that it actually makes three, so two does the fact that aggression is evil,
not prevent people from erroneously acting on the thought that it is good. Furthermore,
Konrad himself states that the NAP forms the outer boundary of justifiability for any norm or rule.
This is because any norm in contradiction to the NAP is simply incoherent via the nature of
justification as such. Law is pointless it is not a subset of ethics. A is a crime, but so what?
What does it mean to have a right if it doesn't mean that it should not be violated? Could one
accept wholesale the NAP and the entire Rothbardian politics, whilst agreeing with every ethical
prescription we hear from the Marxists? If ethics and the law merely intersect, where do the intersect
and why not elsewhere? What are those rights that should be violated and in what sense are they even
rights if they shouldn't be respected? A favorite quote of the ethics and law separators comes from Hoppe himself
QUOTE, who states, the praxeological proof of libertarianism has the advantage of
offering a completely value free justification of private property, it remains entirely in the
realm of his statements and never tries to derive an alt from an is. The structure of this argument
is this. A, justification is propositional justification, a priori true is statement.
B, argumentation presupposes property in one's body and the homesteading principle,
a priori true is statement. And C, then no deviation from this ethic can be argumentatively justified,
a priori true is statement. The proof also offers a key to an understanding of the nature of the
fact of value dichotomy. Ought statements cannot be derived from his statements, they belong to
different logical realms. It is also clear, however, that one cannot even state that there are facts
and values if no propositional exchanges exist. And at this practice of propositional exchanges,
in turn, presupposes the acceptance of the private property ethic as valid. In other words,
END QUOTE cognition and truth seeking as such have a normative foundation, and the normative foundation on
Hoppe is indeed correct that his above syllogism as not of the form
is-statement, is-statement, therefore, ought-statement. But those in the Konrad camp
are incorrect to conclude from this that argumentation ethics fails to demonstrate
the truth and falsehood of different ought statements, as Hoppe himself stated in that very passage,
recognition of the private property ethic aka the NAP, as valid, is a precondition for arguing
over anything. Thus, to try and dispute the NAP, you have to first accept that it is true,
giving it the axiomatic status just as surely as the action axiom or the law of non-contradiction.
Furthermore, we can use a conclusion of Hoppe's above syllogism to construct a new syllogism.
1. I ought engage in aggression X implies a contradiction. A priori true is statement.
2. Contradictions are false. A priori true is statement.
In other words, the negation of the NAP implies a contradiction. Therefore, the negation of
the negation of the NAP, which is the NAP, is true. But how could this be if
fact and values "belong to different logical realms?"
The issue we come to with this view is a dogmatic application of Hume's guillotine,
also called the fact-value dichotomy. The claim is that it is impossible to
drive an ought from an is, but clearly I have done just that. The negation of the NAP is an
ought statement that implies a contradiction. Contradictions are false, therefore the NAP is true.
It is a true ought statement. However, you want to describe this, whether I have sidesteped or
transcended or ploughed straight through Hume's guillotine. The fact remains that there are true
values, and thus there is no dichotomy between facts and values. This statement is incredibly
controversial in the face of modern subjectivist philosophy. Where insofar as ethics is even
thought about, it is dismissed out of hand as a mere description of what people want to do.
But of course, saying that person A wants to do X over not X is the claim that A thinks he
should pick X over not X when given the chance. That is to say, a preference for X over not X
is itself an ethical claim, so choice itself has value implications. I imagine almost everyone
takes the is-ought gap for granted, thus I will take some time to further elaborate on why the fact
value dichotomy does not exist. First, values in the ethical sense are not arbitrary.
Insofar as a person is engaging in any form of evaluation or making some argument or acting
at all, he is necessarily making the choice of existence over non-existence. That is to say,
to remain in reality, to claim anything to be correct at all, he must hold life as a value.
To negate the value of life would be to immediately contradict oneself, as said negation would have
to be performed by a living man who chooses to keep living for the purpose of uttering his negation.
The good, therefore, corresponds to that which is pro-life, and the bad, that which is anti-life.
Furthermore, man is not an automaton. He evaluates because he chooses. The choice he has at any
crossroads is whether to be pro-life, i.e. in correspondence to reality, or anti-life, i.e.
not in correspondence to reality. In other words, a man always has the choice whether to accept truth,
to think, or to reject truth, to evade it. Because evading reality is itself a rejection of truth,
one cannot coherently argue for evasion, as this would involve making the truth claim that there
is no such thing as truth, to which all one can ask, is it true that there is no such thing as truth?
Because evasion or pro-falsehood is anti-life, and life is undeniably good, evasion is undeniably
bad. In other words, any is statement implies a set of ought statements, and vice versa.
Making a moral claim implies presuppositions about epistemology and metaphysics, and making
claims about epistemology and metaphysics necessarily implies certain things about ethics.
QUOTE In the objective approach, since every fact bears them the choice to live, every truth
necessarily entails a value judgment, and every value judgment necessarily presupposes a truth.
As Ayn Rand states the point in the objectivist ethics, knowledge for any conscious organism
is the means for survival. To live in consciousness, every is implies an ought.
Evaluation, accordingly, is not a compartmentalized function,
applicable only to some aspect of a man's life or of reality.
END QUOTE If one chooses to live, and to be objective, a process of evaluation is co-extensive with,
That is, facts about reality, such as that the sun shines or that lightning strikes,
have implications for man's self-preservation, and because man
objectively ought endeavour to preserve himself, these metaphysically given facts implies certain
things about what man should be doing. The fact that the sun shines and that within certain limits,
sunshine is good for man, implies all sorts of oughts. For instance, other things being equal,
we ought grow our crops in the shine rather than the shade, because doing so will yield
more crops, and thus further man's life more than the alternative. Also, we ought build our
houses such that they have windows and we can get vitamin D, but sunlight can also cause us damage
by burning our skin if we get too much of it, so other things being equal, we ought avoid
this outcome, possibly wearing sunscreen or bringing an umbrella for shade. All these
evaluations are demanded by the cognitions involved. Again, because these things are pro-life,
they are pro-truth and reality, therefore these oughts cannot be coherently negated. Moreover,
to attempt to negate such an ought is indicative of an error in the thinker in question. They are
either making an honest mistake or they are on an active rebellion against truth. Because error
is bad, to embrace an error as fully as does the thinker an active rebellion against truth, implies
that the proper moral evaluation of this thinker is that he is wicked. Now, this is not the case
for all such instances of perpetuating of falsehood. Men are capable of making honest
mistakes in their understanding of reality. This is most prevalent in the very young or
the intellectually impaired. This is quite distinct to the academic Marxists and other subjectivists who
dedicate their lives to the perpetuation of intellectually dishonest ideas.
QUOTE conscious attempt to perceive reality by the use of one's mind is the essence of honesty,
no such rebellion could qualify as honest. The originators, leaders, and intellectual
spokesman of all such movements are necessarily evaders on a major scale. They are not merely
mistaken, but are crusading irrationalists. The mass base of such movements are not
evaders of the same kind, but most of the followers are dishonest in their own passive way. They
are unthinking intellectually irresponsible, ballast, unconcerned with logic or truth.
They go along with corrupt trendsetters because their neighbours demand it, and or because
a given notion satisfies some out-of-context desire they happen to feel. People of this kind
are not the helplessly ignorant, but the wheelfully self-deluded. Even in regard to inherently
dishonest movements, let me now add, a marginal third category of adherence as possible.
There are a relatively small number whose struggle haunts you anxiously, but simply
cannot grasp the issues and monument or corruption involved. These are a handful of became communists,
channelers, etc., through a truly honest error of knowledge, leaving aside the retarded and
illiterate who are effectively helpless in such matters. This third group consists almost exclusively
of the very young, and precisely for this reason, these youngsters get out of such movements fast,
on their own, without needing lectures from others. They get out of the rich maturity.
Being conscientious and mentally active, they see first-hand what is going on in the movement
and identify what it means, so their initial enthusiasm turns to dismay and then to our,
andray and we the living may be taken as a fictional symbol here. The very honesty of such
individuals limits their stay in the movement. They can't tolerate for long the massiveness
of the evil with which they have become involved, nor when such youngsters drop out. They say to
the world, belligerently, don't dare judge me from my past, because my error was honest.
On the contrary, and here I speak from my own personal experience of honest errors that I
commit to as a teenager, the best among these young people are contrite. They recognise
aid and comfort, inadvertent though it be, which they've been given to error and evil, and they seek
to make amends for it. They expect those who know of their past creates and allegiances to
regard to a suspicion. They know that it is their own responsibility to demonstrate objectively and
END QUOTE across time that they have changed, that they will not repeat their error tomorrow in another
Any form of ethical subjectivism, which is required for the fact-value dichotomy to stand,
implies an epistemology that holds that mere whims are the proper source of evaluation.
This would make ethics, and therefore a law, a completely pointless field
with no reason for existing. That is to say, reacting to Hume's guillotine implies the complete
destruction of ethics to the chattering applause of the most evil philosophies known to man. But
as Hoppe points out, there are certain norms, namely property rights, that must be accepted as
valid prior to beginning any ethical deliberation whatsoever, even an ethical deliberation that seeks
to destroy ethics. Therefore, any ethical theorist who attempts to erect a dichotomy between fact
and value must accept as valid certain values whilst attempting to demonstrate the invalidity of
value as such. So a philosopher qua ethical theorist cannot speak of Hume's guillotine
without falling into utter incoherence, and thus ethical subjectivism is an incoherent
anti-ethics. The immorality of error in one's understanding of the metaphysically given,
such as that the sun shines, or that gravity causes objects fall, pales in comparison to the
immorality present whenever there are errors in man-made facts, consider a world of total
unreason in philosophy. Such a world would imply mass death and suffering of the worst kinds,
as all men would be acting as did Mao and Hitler and Stalin. No matter the level of technological
development, such as society would be incapable of supporting human life. On the contrary,
a far more technologically primitive society, that accepts entirely reason and objective reality,
would find barely any natural disaster that could not be withstood. The standard of living
in such society would quickly soar, where the opposite is true of the irrational society.
QUOTE To an individual and divisional labour society, it makes it a way for death different, whether
he's surrounded by producers or parasites, honest men or cheats, independent men or power
lustres. Just as one must distinguish being good and bad in relation to the realm of nature,
so one must distinguish being good and bad in relation to the realm of man.
In objective terms, this means a single fundamental issue. In the human realm, one must distinguish
the rational from the irrational. The thinker is from the aviators, such a judgment tells one
whether a man, in principle, is committed to reality, or to escaping from and fighting it.
In one case, he's an ally and potential benefactor of the living, in the other, an enemy and potential
destroyer, thus the mandate of justice. Identify the good, the rational, and the evil, the irrational,
END QUOTE in men and their works. Then first, deal with, support, and or reward the good. And second,
So the proper moral evaluation of an idea, or more broadly a philosophy,
is that it's good insofar as it promotes human flourishing.
And bad, insofar as it does the opposite. This evaluation is not based on an arbitrary whim
of the evaluator. It is not the claim that the idea or philosophy in question is merely
distasteful to the man making the evaluation. An objective evaluation must make reference
to the objective and undeniable value of life itself.
QUOTE is a positive moral estimate of the mental processes that led to it,
a credit to the individual for having worked to grasp reality, and a positive estimate of the
existential results to come. A true idea will have to yield poor life results when men act on it,
the same applies mutatus butanis to false ideas. Implicit in seeing that an idea contradicts the
facts of reality, is a negative estimate of the processes that led to it, and also of the effects
that the idea will have in practice, which have to be to harmful. If one's ideas are tied to reality
at all, and if one is guided by life as a standard, there is no way to identify an idea's truth or
falsehood without it in some form also making such evaluations. Truth is a product of effort,
and leads to inaction to values. Hence, when it says the idea is not only true, it is also good.
Faucet, assuming it reaches a certain scale, is a product of evasion, and leads to destruction.
Such an idea is not only false, it is also evil. An employee, to take a relatively modest
positive example, offers a man an idea for improving the operation of his business.
His idea, thus concludes after weighing the evidence, takes into account all the relevant
facts. He's right, so far this is a pure cognition, the outcome of which is expressed in a statement
like, I agree with you. When a decent person, whether he knew his philosophy or not, would stop there,
he would not say unemotionally like a dead fish, your idea is correct, good day. On the contrary,
precisely because the new idea represents a new grasp of reality, the moral kind of boss is
enthusiastic, he evaluates the idea, he can't avoid seeing two things, this employee of mine had
to innovate, struggle, think, to reach the idea when no one else did, and the idea will cut my
costs, increase my customers, double my profits. The boss accordingly is excited, he likes the
employee, he praises him, he rewards him, he not only says about the idea, true, as an inevitable
END QUOTE corollary, he says about it, good, that good is the evaluation or the ought, he represents the
Thus it is completely inescapable that true is-statements
imply true evaluations related to those statements, and false is-statements imply
false evaluations related to those statements, just as it is an error for the primitive man to
attempt to make it rain by dancing, it is an error to commit murder or steal a wallet,
these actions are bad because they are destructive of life and human flourishing,
it is impossible to construct a rational property norm where aggression is allowed,
and just as the fact that the rain dancer is acting an error is not negated by the fact that he is
still capable of performing the rain dance, nor is the fact that the murderer is acting in error
negated by the fact that he is still capable of murder, it is incoherent to claim any crime to
be a moral virtue, as every crime implies an evasion of objective law, and evasions are
per se errors and errors are per se immoral, the true is the good, and the good is the true.