2. The non-aggression principle
Corconition and truth seeking as such have a value normative foundation, and the normative
foundation on which cognition and truth rest is the recognition of private property rights
In the previous lesson we discovered some necessary facts about the nature of law,
We know that there must be a universal objective law, and we know that
the normative structure of law must be based upon the normative structure of argumentation.
In this lesson, the central norm, the core axiom of true law, will be made explicit.
We call this central axiom the non-aggression principle, or NAP, and it can be stated
as follows. The non-aggressor ought be the director, or that the aggressor ought not
be the director. These statements are contrapositive. Let's break that down. Here, aggression
is defined as the initiation of conflict, so in any contest over some property alpha,
if A is the aggressor and B is the non-aggressor, B ought to be the one to direct the use of
alpha and A ought not. The term axiom has a precise meaning in philosophy. Unlike in mathematics
where axioms are merely inter-consistent but arbitrarily chosen rules, praxeological axioms
are self-evident propositions. A proposition is self-evident if you must accept its validity
in attempting to dispute its validity. We saw above how the law of non-contradiction
is a self-evident proposition. In disputing anything at all, you must first accept that
the law of non-contradiction holds. Similarly, in disputing the NAP, you presuppose its truth,
as it is implied by the very nature of argumentation. First, recall that argumentation does not
exist in a normative void. That is to say, there are certain norms which are presupposed
in the very act of arguing. Consider what it would mean for this to not be the case.
If argumentation had no particular normative structure, it would lose any meaning. Literally
any action a man takes could be considered an argumentation, such as eating an apple
or swinging from a tree, or shooting someone through the head. It is because of
the fact that certain norms define a dialectic as such, there is such a thing called argumentation
in the first place. Second, the validity of any truth claim must be raised and decided
upon in the course of an argumentation, so the normative structure of argumentation in
particular has a special status being the practical precondition for ascertaining
the truth or validity of any statement. This is known as the a priori of argumentation,
which is another self-evident proposition. If you were to dispute it, you would first
have to start arguing, thus presupposing its truth. Third, to try and argumentatively
dispute one of the norms of argumentation would be to contradict oneself. This is called
a dialectic or a performative contradiction. That is, it is a contradiction not between
propositions but between a proposition and the very act of proposing it. For instance,
if one were to argue that people ought never argue, they would first presuppose that they
should be arguing, thus they are in contradiction. Therefore, the negation of people ought never
argue, which is people ought ever argue, or people ought sometimes argue, must be correct.
Of note here is that under argumentation ethics, the "sometimes" is not an arbitrary when I feel
like it. It is something more like people should argue to resolve disputes, rather than
people should engage in conflict to resolve disputes. This is because, fourth, argumentation
is a conflict-free interaction. Interlocutors have some dispute over the truth of the matter,
and they are seeking to convince the other, not through the force of violence, i.e., by
aggressing against them, but rather through the force of their argument. Specifically,
argumentation is a method of resolving disputes peacefully, not violently. Consider A and B have a dispute
over who has the property right to Alpha. A asserts that they are the owner, and vice
versa. Arguing over this dispute would not involve the two parties violently attacking
each other. It would involve the exchange of propositions with the intent of determining
the truth of the matter. Simply warring over Alpha would not be truth-seeking. Interpersonal
warfare does not involve argumentative justification, and argumentative justification does not involve
interpersonal warfare. This means that the normative structure of argumentation implies
non-aggression. Thus, the NAP is dialectically true. Consider what it would mean to say
that this is not the case, that violence is perfectly permissible in an argument.
If Crusoe has a disagreement with Friday, and Crusoe decides that he will beat Friday
until agreement is reached, is Crusoe really seeking the truth of the matter here? Clearly
he is not. Coercing others to not argue with you cannot tend to establish truth. Warfare
of this sort is the enemy of reason. Insofar as a man is engaged in unreason, i.e., avoiding
truth, he cannot coherently make any truth claim. Thus, no negation of any proposition
can arise from unreason. You have to accept reason, in order to argue at all, and accepting
reason means accepting the NAP. It certainly cannot be denied that the purpose of argumentation
is to seek truth on the matter. So such aggressive activities that do not tend to establish truth
must be excluded from arguments. In short, argumentation is a rational activity, and
aggression is the enemy of reason. Thus, these sets of actions must be mutually exclusive.
All true propositions are justifiable argumentatively. A true ethic is justifiable to an arguer.
Justifiability is irrelevant in a conflict. A conflict cannot be justified to an arguer.
If it could, there will be no conflict. Hence, causing conflicts is against the ethics of argumentation.
QUOTE Looked at from another angle, participants in argumentation indisputably
need to use and control the scarce resources in the world to survive. Otherwise, they
would perish. But because their scarcity makes conflict over the use of resource as possible,
only norms that determine the proper ownership can avoid conflict over these scarce goods.
That such norms are valuable cannot be denied, because anyone who is alive in the world on
participating in the practical activity of argumentation cannot deny the value of being
END QUOTE able to control scarce resources and the value of avoiding conflicts over such scarce resources.
A further proof of the existence of rights is found by considering what it would mean
to deny that rights exist. Kinsella introduces the concept as follows:
END QUOTE exists, it is a right of A to have or do X without B's preventing it, and therefore
A can legitimately use force against B to enforce the right. A is concerned with the
enforceability of his right to X, and this enforceability is all that A requires in order
to be secure in his right to X. For a right skeptic, meaningfully, to a challenge A is
asserted right, the skeptic must challenge the enforceability of the right, instead of
merely challenging the existence of the right. Nothing less will do. If the skeptic does
not deny that A's post-enforcement of his purported right is legitimate, then the skeptic
has not denied A's right to X, because what it means to have a right is to be able to
legitimately enforce it. If the skeptic maintains then that A has no right to X, indeed no rights
END QUOTE at all since there are no rights, the skeptic must also maintain that A's enforcement of
This presents a problem for the rights-sceptic, however,
because he must hold that enforcement, i.e. the use of force, requires justification,
but merely challenging A's use of force is not enough. The rights-sceptic can't just
express distaste at the enforcement, he must attack the legitimacy of said use of force.
But in order to challenge the legitimacy of A using force against B to enforce the right,
he must hold that B has a right to not have this force against him, i.e. that B or someone
else can legitimately use force to stop A's use of force, but then he is in contradiction,
as he must recognize rights held by B in his denial that rights exist.
QUOTE this demonstration points out the inconsistency on the part of a right skeptic who engages
in discourse about the propriety of rights at all. If there are no rights, then there's
no such thing as the justifiable or legitimate use of force, but neither is there such a
thing as the unjust use of force. But if there is no unjust use of force, what is it exactly
that a right skeptic is concerned about? If individuals delude themselves into thinking
that they have natural rights and acting on this assumption go by enforcing these rights
as if they are true, the skeptic has no grounds to complain. To the extent that the skeptic
complains about people enforcing these illusory rights, he begins to attribute rights to those
having forces against them. Any right skeptic can only shut up, because he contradicts himself
the moment he objects to others acting as if they have rights. Indeed, another way to
respond to a right skeptic would be to propose to physically harm him. If there are no rights
as he maintains, then he cannot object to being harmed. So presumably any right skeptic would
change his position and admit that there were rights, if only so as to be able to object
END QUOTE to being harmed, or there would soon be no more right skeptics left alive to give rights
A somewhat common question raised with respect to the non-aggression
principle is whether the mob boss who merely orders his goons to engage in some aggression
is himself an aggressor. The answer to this question is yes. Both he and his goons are
engaged in the aggression in question. To highlight why this is the case, consider that
a crime is an action. It is the use of efficacious means to cause the invasion of the borders
of other people's property. Because such an invasion initiates conflict between the
criminal and the victim. What is important here is that you can use other people as means
towards some end. In the provided example, the mob boss is using his goons as a means
to cause the invasion of the victim's property, and the goons are using their hands or some
weapons as a means to the same end. Both the boss and his goons are engaged in the same
aggressive invasion. Consider the example of a man shipping a bomb to a victim's house
using a courier. The bomb blows up upon the victim opening the package. Has the bomb maker
committed a crime here? Well, if using other people as means is to break the chain of causation,
then perhaps the courier is the criminal, as he is the one who delivered the bomb. But
even this cannot be so, because the bomb only went off upon the victim opening the package.
So really, the victim has committed suicide! Of course, this is ridiculous. The bomb maker
is well aware that paying a courier to deliver a package to someone is likely to result in
said package being opened. The courier and the victim are both being used as a means
towards the end of the victim exploding. This is the intent of the bomb maker.
QUOTE positive law recognised that an intervening force only breaks the causal connection when
it is unforeseeable. As the restatement of Torz provides, the intervention of a force
which is a normal consequence of a situation created by the actor's conduct is not a superseding
cause of harm, which such conduct has been a substantial factor in bringing about. Clearly,
when the terrorist in these cases uses a courier to deliver a later bomb, it is not unforeseeable
END QUOTE that the victim will receive it, and it is not unforeseeable that the victim will open
This is because, if the outcome of a given activity was truly unforeseeable, this implies
it is not an action. As for it to be an action, it has to be deliberately aimed at and sought
after. Consider me leaving a knife on my kitchen counter that is then whipped away by a tornado
and thus stabs a man through the heart. I didn't stab him, the tornado did, because
the tornado was unforeseeable by me. If I was a wizard, who could control tornadoes and
I summoned the tornado to throw my knife into the heart of the man, that would be foreseeable
and therefore criminal. In other words, A simply hoping that lightning will strike B is different
to A knowing exactly when and where lightning will strike and duping B into standing there at the appropriate time.
There is no intention if the outcome is only hoped for.
To make this even more clear, consider the example of a rifle that requires 3 men to shoot, perhaps
it has 3 triggers which are far apart on which all must be pulled to fire the bullet. If
3 men conspire to each pull a trigger, at the same time to shoot an innocent man, then
all 3 of them are engaged in an aggression against this person. We can trivially
analogise this to a bomber plane that requires 3 men to operate. One to steer the plane,
one to load the bombs, and a third to trigger the release of the bombs. It is not only the
man who triggers the release, but also his two co-conspirators, who are each engaged in the
action of bombing with the bomber plane. Insofar as this bombing is an aggression,
all 3 men are equally liable for this crime. This is why the getaway driver in a bank
robbery is just as liable for the theft as his partners who restrained the crowd and stole
the funds from the vault respectively. Furthermore, if in the process of the robbery, the crowd
controller shoots one of the hostages, the getaway driver and the safe cracker are responsible
for this murder, because the murder is understood to be a part of the entire robbery going
forth. If instead they were not robbing a bank, which involves threatening hostages
with death, but rather jointly attempting to steal a car, then one of the car thieves
randomly sets off a bomb killing countless individuals, then only the bomber is responsible.
Setting off the bomb is a separate action to the stealing of the cars, so the co-conspirators
to the car theft are not responsible for it. To reiterate this point, allow me to quote Kinsella.
QUOTE Consider the following example, and our content, A, purchases a remote controlled
tank, with a remote control he can steer the tank and fire its cannon. He directs the tank
to blow down the walls of his neighbour's house, destroying the house and killing the
neighbour. No one would deny that A is the cause of the killing and is guilty of murder
and trespass. However, after the rampage, a hatch opens up in the tank and an evil midget
jumps out. It turns out, you see, that the midget could see on the screen which buttons
were pressed on the remote control, and he would operate the tank accordingly. We submit
that A is equally liable in both cases. From his point of view, the tank was a black box
END QUOTE that he used to attain his end. Regardless of whether there is a human will, somewhere
This black box thinking is crucial;
consider what would happen if it was discovered someday that firearms
are actually sentient and capable of choosing not to accept a trigger press, and that this
is the cause of bullet jams. Would this suddenly absolve everyone who has used a firearm to
kill another of any criminal responsibility? Surely not. None of these people knew that
firearms were sentient and could refuse to shoot. To the gunman, the firearm is a means
towards the end of shooting a bullet at their victim. This does not change if it is later
discovered that firearms have a mind of their own.
QUOTE means it is illegal to cause another person to be hit. That is to say, it is illegal to
use physical objects, including one's fist, in a way that will cause the unwanted physical
contact with another person. In analyzing actions through the lens of praxiological means and
structure to determine if it amounts to aggression, we ask if the actor employed means to achieve
the end of invading the borders of another's property or body. In other words, we ask
if he caused the border invasion. The means employed can be inanimate or nonhuman means,
governed solely by causal laws, agan, or it can include other humans who are employed
as means to achieve the illicit end desire. The latter category includes both innocent
END QUOTE humans that one employs to cause a border invasion and culpable humans that one conspires, co-operates
We can use this analysis to highlight the guilt of Henry II of England,
who reportedly exclaimed, "will no one rid me of this turbulent priest?"
to a group of knights under his employ. The turbulent priest referred to the Archbishop
of Canterbury, who had excommunicated a number of bishops supportive of the king. Four of
the king's knights upon hearing the king's utterance went to the Archbishop and murdered
him. The argument is that the king's words, though
not literally worded as an order, nevertheless communicated to his knights that he wished
for them to carry out the ridding of the priest. What this highlights is the importance of
communication in libertarian theory. The king is using his knights that he means because
he is communicating to them his desire for them to kill or otherwise coerce the priest.
What this shows is that social norms and understanding of language can influence whether
a given set of words demonstrate an aggression or not. So it may be the case that if I'm
in a seedy bar and I go up to the biggest, toughest guy in there and call his mother a whore,
I am in fact communicating to him that I want a fight. Or another case is when I have a
mailbox on my front door and a path leading to it. This can be seen as communicating to
couriers that I want them to deliver packages by walking up to my door over my path and
placing packages inside the mailbox. This demonstrates the limits of what Kinsella dubs
armchair theorizing. One cannot say with certainty whether a given action is aggression without
having all the relevant information provided, which is why judges are necessary in a rational
legal system. The judge is able to analyze all the relevant details to determine who
is at fault. The job of the jurist sitting in his armchair is to explicate objective
principles and perhaps to apply them to very simple hypothetical scenarios where all the
relevant details can be provided.