3. Homesteading and property rights
The first user and possessor of a good is either its owner or his not. If he's not,
then who is? The person who takes it from him by force? If forcefully taking possession
from a prior owner entitles the new possessor to that thing, then there is no such thing
as ownership, but only mere possession. But such a rule that a later user may acquire
something by taking it from the previous owner does not avoid conflicts, it rather authorizes
them. Stephan Kinsella.
Now that the non-aggression principle has been demonstrated as an apodictically correct
axiom of law, some initial implications can be derived, the first of which is the homesteading
principle, which can be stated as ownership is assigned to the initial possessor/director
of any external good, where homesteading is defined as initial possession. Note, it
is not particularly irrelevant whether you define homesteading as initial possession or
initial direction. The initial possessor of the good is the one who initially directs
the use of it. However, I prefer the terminology of direction, in most cases, as will be made
clear later. You will often see this described as the prior later distinction.
That is, the homesteading principle gives precedence to the first-comer over any late-comers.
Consider Crusoe and Friday, stranded on a desert island. Crusoe comes across a stick
in nature and homesteads it, i.e. takes initial possession of it. Then he fashions it into
a spear which he plans to use for spearfishing. On his way to the ocean, however, Friday sees
this stick and thinks it would be a useful tool to stoke his fire, and so he attempts
to repossess it, that is, take it from Crusoe. We have a conflict. Crusoe can't spearfish
at the same time that Friday stokes his fire, and it is intuitively clear that Friday has
initiated this conflict. First, it must be noted that ownership is necessarily distinct
from direction, and this is presupposed as true by both Crusoe and Friday. In asserting
different ownership claims, they are saying that they are the ones who justly direct
the use of the stick, i.e., if someone else tries to do so, that is unjust. We know this
because ownership itself is defined as just direction. Kinsella points out that
the fact that ownership and direction are distinct implies that only the first possession/direction
is justifiable. If B can become the owner of a thing merely by taking it from
A, this means that C could take it from B and thereby become the owner. This would mean
that the actual ability to direct the use of a thing and ownership of that thing are
not distinct. Whoever is able to control a stick would be the owner, and this contradicts
the presumption by all parties that ownership and direction are distinct. Therefore, as
it is a contradiction to propose that a latecomer has a property right, we are left with the
initial director having the only justifiable claims of property right. Initial direction
is the only just direction, and therefore is only the homestead who has the unique status
of ownership. In other words, we can see not only that locking homesteading is inextricably
bound up with a prior later distinction, but that the very idea of ownership implies that
only libertarian-style ownership is justifiable. So, property rights are conflict-avoiding norms
and assigned to the first-comer rather than any late-comer, and from this fact we can
derive a corollary about the nature of a legitimate homesteading claim, namely that the borders
of said homesteaded property must be objective and intersubjectively ascertainable. This fact
becomes clear when we break it down into its constituent parts. First, the borders of a
homesteaded property must be objective, that is, they must adhere to existence as against
the arbitrary content of one's consciousness. This is because subjective property borders
might contradict, and thus a subjective system of property rights is irrational, and could
not make for universal law. You will recall that law must be universal and objective to
be rational. Consider a system of property rights based upon such arbitrary decrees.
For example, A having the right to punch B, but B not having the right to punch A. This
system would not be objective. Neither A nor B could rationally derive such a rule, and
as such, you could not be expected to follow it. What this means is that an arbitrary system
of property rights like this cannot avoid conflicts, it would rather authorize them.
Now we turn to the criterion that property borders must be intersubjectively ascertainable.
What this means is that they are "public," and can be seen or in some other way perceived
by third parties. The reason why rational property borders must be intersubjectively
ascertainable is that if they are not, they cannot serve to avoid conflicts, and property
rights are conflict avoiding norms. Consider a non-intersubjectively ascertainable property
border, such as a mere verbal decree. Robinson Crusoe decides that he wants to own the moon,
so he simply shouts to the forest that he now owns the moon. Clearly, this verbal decree
cannot serve to avoid conflicts. When an astronaut is approaching the moon, he has no means of
discovering Crusoe's supposed property right in the moon. Thus, Crusoe has not actually
homesteaded the moon, he has not erected an objective, intersubjectively ascertainable border.
No one could ever deny that norms for determining the ownership of scarce goods are useful for
allowing conflict-free exploitation of such resources. But, as Hoppe points out, there
are only two fundamental alternatives for acquiring unowned property.
One, by doing something with things which no one else had ever done anything before,
that is the Lockean concept of mixing labour, or homesteading, or two, by verbal declaration
or decree. However, a rule that allows property to be owned by mere verbal declaration cannot
serve to avoid conflicts, since any number of people could, at any time, assert conflicting
claims of ownership of a particular scarce resource. Only the first alternative, that
of Lockean homesteading, establishes an objective link between a particular person
and a particular scarce resource. And thus, no one can deny the Lockean right to homestead
unowned resources. What these criteria for rational property borders highlight is that
communication lies at the very root of law. In homesteading a particular scarce resource,
you have to be able to somehow communicate to others that you are using it. If you fail
at this, you fail at your task of homesteading, and cannot be said to own the thing in the
first place. An important edge-case must be analysed for this theory to be complete.
Namely, the instance of Crusoe and Friday simultaneously attempting to take possession
of a stick in nature. Clearly, neither came prior to the other, so it is improper to describe
either as the first- or late-comer. In this situation, Crusoe and Friday are in a stalemate,
where the term stalemate is used to indicate that it is not a conflict. From the definition
of the hypothetical, we know that neither Crusoe nor Friday have actually started engaging
in their chosen action with the stick. As in the first instance, the stick was in nature,
then in the very next, both Crusoe and Friday made an attempt to begin acting with it. This
attempt is not yet complete, and the action has not yet started until the other backs
off. Such a stalemate situation may turn into a conflict if either Crusoe or Friday forcefully
excludes the other from completing their homesteading of the stick. This is a situation
of the forceful one, say Crusoe, excluding the other from that which he does not own. This
is an invasion from Crusoe against Friday, therefore Crusoe is the aggressor and not
the proper owner of the stick. Clearly, there is now a conflict over the use of the stick,
else Crusoe would not be excluding Friday from the stick, but from something else, and it is
Crusoe who has initiated this conflict. Thus, to forcefully exclude the other in a stalemate
situation is to disqualify yourself from ownership of the good under stalemate, thereby
ceding ownership to the other. The simpler case is when either Crusoe or Friday decide
that they will back off on their own, thus non-aggressively breaking the stalemate and
ceding ownership to the other more stubborn man. Now we must turn our attention to the
Georgist anti-homestead ethic, which would claim that the first possessor also doesn't
have the ownership right, and in fact the homesteading itself is a crime against everyone
else. This ethic fails in the grounds of its very proposal. To engage in an argumentation,
one must first homestead something, at the very least their standing room. Before beginning
any ethical deliberation, you must therefore accept it to be just, that is to say argumentatively
justifiable, to take initial possession and to therefore initially direct the use of some
scarce physical means. Hoppe explains that a late-comer ethic implies the death of humanity.
What is wrong with this idea of dropping the prior later distinction as morally irrelevant?
First, if the late-comers, i.e. those who did not in fact do something with some scarce
goods, had indeed as much of a right to the most first-comers, i.e. those who did do
something with the scarce goods, then literally no one would be allowed to do anything with
anything, as one would have to have all of the late-comers consent prior to doing whatever
one wanted to do. Indeed, as posterity would include one's children's children, people
that is, who come so late that one could never possibly ask them. Advocating a legal
system that does not make use of the prior later distinction as part of its underlying
property theory is simply absurd in that it implies advocating death but must presuppose
life in order to advocate anything. Neither we, our forefathers, nor our progeny could,
do, or will survive and say or argue anything if one were to follow this rule. In order
for any person, past, present, or future, to argue anything, it must be possible to survive
now. No one can wait and suspend acting until everyone of an indeterminate class of late-comers
happens to appear and agree to what one wants to do. Rather, insofar as a person finds
himself alone, he must be able to act, to use, produce, consume goods straight away. Prior
to any agreement with people who are simply not around yet, and perhaps never will be.
And insofar as a person finds himself in the company of others, and there is conflict
over how to use a given scarce resource, he must be able to resolve the problem at a definite
point in time with a definite number of people, instead of having to wait unspecified periods
of time for unspecified numbers of people. Simply in order to survive then, which is
a prerequisite to arguing in favour of or against anything, property rights cannot be
conceived of as being timeless and nonspecific regarding the number of people concerned. Rather,
they must necessarily be thought of as originating through acting at definite points in time
for definite acting individuals. Furthermore, the idea of abandoning the priorly to distinction,
which socialism finds so attractive, would again simply be incompatible with the non-aggression
principle as the practical foundation of argumentation. To argue and possibly agree
with someone, if only on the fact that there is disagreement, means to recognise each other
prior right of exclusive control over his own body. Otherwise, it would be impossible
for anyone to first say anything at a definite point in time, and for someone else to then
be able to reply or vice versa, as neither the first nor the second speaker would be independent
physical decision-making units any more at any time. Eliminating the prior later distinction
then, as socialism attempts to do, is tantamount to eliminating the possibility of arguing and
reaching agreement. However, as one cannot argue that there is no possibility for discussion
without the prior control of every person over his own body being recognised and accepted
as fair, a late-comer ethic that does not wish to make this difference could never be agreed
upon by anyone, simply saying that it could imply the contradiction, as ones being able
to say so would presuppose one's existence as an independent decision-making unit at
a definite point in time. Above, the homestead principle was defined as ownership as assigned
to the initial possessor/director of any external good. This is important because
the above analysis only works for goods which are external to the body of an acting man, and
it assumes that there are already acting men going into nature and extracting various
goods from it. A person's body is an entirely different type of object. There aren't bodies
out in nature waiting for some soul to come along and homestead them. Rather, a body is
necessarily linked to an actor. It is this objective link which imbues a man with ownership. Homesteading
is merely one form of demonstrating this link. So how do we deal with the case of establishing
links between acting men and the bodies used for action? Recall that property rights in
general are conflict avoiding norms. That is to say, the very nature of ownership is
to avoid conflicts. Recall also that this was derived from the nature of argumentation
itself, so we can go back to argumentation to derive an assignment of property rights
in bodies. For A and B to argue with each other, they have to first assume that the other
guy owns himself. Imagine if A tried to argue that B is actually owned by C. Well, this
would mean that B would be a mere mouthpiece for C, and thus A would actually be arguing
with C, which contradicts the presumption that A is arguing with B. Therefore, you could
never propose that someone else is a slave without contradiction. In trying to demonstrate
to this man that he is your or someone else's slave, you would have to first assume that
he owns himself, then propose that you or someone else owns him, i.e. that he does
not own himself. In other words, to engage in any argument whatsoever, you have to first
accept the validity of other men's claim to direct the use of their body. Argumentation
becomes impossible to the degree that you reject the validity of this. Consider also
the discussion above of the importance of property borders being objective and intersubjectively
ascertainable. An implication of this is that particularistic norms such as A being allowed
to a punch B, but not the other way around, are false. Similarly, an arbitrary notion
of one group owning another group must also be discarded. This is because you have an
objective, undeniable-and-thus-intersubjectively-ascertainable link to your own body. To
enslave someone, the only way to control their body is indirectly via coercion, either physical
or via threat, to get them to act how you want. In this case, the slave is still the
one directly controlling their body, which is a superior link to the indirect one that
the enslaver has. If arbitrarily coercing others to do what you wanted, constituted a
greater claim over the body of the coerced person, it would be impossible to avoid conflicts
over bodies. We would rather have a system of might-making right, which is a conflict
authorising system of property, and thus not a rational system of property at all. The
enslaver also contradicts himself by recognising the precedence of this link over his own body
by using his body to coerce his slave. Moreover, any outsider who claims another's body cannot
deny this objective link and its special status, since the outsider also necessarily
presupposes this in his own case. This is so, because in seeking dominion over the other,
in asserting ownership over the other's body, he has to presuppose his own ownership of his body,
which demonstrates that he does place a certain significance on this link, at the same time
that he disregards the significance of the other's link to his own body. Furthermore,
we consider that a slavery ethic, i.e., an ethic which rejects self-ownership, cannot
make for a human ethic. To be an ethic for humanity, it must satisfy two properties. First,
it must be universal, i.e., it must apply to all humans, and second, it must actually
ensure the survival of mankind, or else it would be an anti-human ethic, and an anti-human ethic could
not be proposed without contradiction, as you must first presume that you should be alive
and arguing. Rothbard has pointed out that if you do not have a system of total self-ownership,
two possibilities remain. One, universal and equal other ownership, which he calls the
communist ethic, or two, partial ownership of one group by another.
Universal co-ownership fails on the grounds that it would imply the near immediate death
of humanity, because for any person to survive they must act, and if everyone is co-owned
by everyone, then any given person must first ask everyone else's permission before engaging
in some action. But asking permission is itself an action. Therefore, everyone must immediately
start doing nothing. Further, it is not strictly possible to purposefully not act. We note
that action is defined as purposeful behaviour, so even in ceasing physical motion a man is
acting, insofar as this ceasing is done purposefully. Therefore, this ethic simply cannot be obeyed
no matter what a man chooses to do, as choosing any option implies action. Partial ownership
of one group by another doesn't necessarily mean the death of humanity, but is not universal.
Instead of being an ethic for humans, it is an ethic which implies a set of subhumans
ruled by humans. This is thus a particularistic ethic. It is a norm of the form, one rule
for thee, and another for me. But if the partial ownership ethic was truly rational, it must
be able to be derived from the nature of the entities that it applies to. Thus, there would
have to be some principled difference between the group of humans and the group of subhumans.
We know that legal ethics are derived from argumentation, and as such they would have
to apply to all beings which have the potential to argue. Therefore, there could be no relevant
difference between different groups of humans with respect to law, as all humans, qua
acting being, have the potential to engage in argumentation. One could come up with any
number of selection criteria to split mankind up into different sets. Perhaps one wants
to split man into different races, or nations, or into northern southern hemispheres, etc.
The point of note here is that these different groups do not have different logics, so any
conclusions derived that apply to arguing beings as such would have to apply to all of them.
Now that we have a theory of property which accounts for both self ownership and external
ownership, we can begin to address some implications of this theory, the first of which is that
ownership is necessarily individual. That is, group ownership is strictly impossible.
Consider a set of people, A through Z, who each commonly own a stick. What has been done about
a conflict over the use of the stick between A and B? There are two possibilities, either
A is said to be the just victor, or B is. If A, then he owns a stick, and B does not.
If B, then he owns a stick, and A does not. But both options contradict the presumption
that every member in the set owns the stick. Therefore, group ownership simply cannot occur.
Allow me to go over some supposed solutions to this conundrum, the first of which is the
democratic one. Essentially, all members within the set vote to determine who the just victor
is. Still, any who lost the vote did not own the stick, as their desired possession was
considered unjust. Also consider the set which consists only of A and B. What vote could
possibly be conducted between these men which would not come out as A in favour of A and
B in favour of B. If B voted for A or vice versa, there would be no conflict, and law
these only those sets of situations where there is conflict rather than those where men are
in a harmonious agreement about how things should be done.
The next proposal for a solution comes from Roderick Long. He states, on the libertarian
view, we have the right to the fruit of our labour, and we also have a right to what
people freely give us. Public property can rise in both these ways. Consider a village
near a lake. It is common for the villagers to walk down to the lake to go fishing. In
the early days of the community, it is hard to get to the lake because of all the bushes
and fallen branches in the way. But over time, the way is cleared and a path forms, not through
any centrally coordinated effort, but simply as a result of all the individuals walking
that way day after day. The cleared path is a product of labour, not any individuals
labour, but all of them together. If one villager decided to take advantage of the now created
path by setting up a gate and charging tools, he would be violating the collective property
right that the villagers together have earned. Public property can also be the product of
gift. In the 19th century England, it was common for roads to be built privately and
then donated to the public for free use. This was done not out of altruism, but because
the road builders owned land and businesses alongside the site of the new road, and they
knew that having a road there would increase the value of their land and attract more customers
to their business. Thus, the unorganized public can legitimately come to own land, both through
original acquisition, the mixing of labour, and through voluntary transfer. So, Long provides
two cases that he sees as legitimate group property; (1) where a group communally mix
their labour with an object in nature, and (2) where a man transfers ownership of his private
property to group in common. The issue with (1) is that Long relies on the faulty labour
theory of property. It is not mixing labour with land which imbues a man with ownership,
as we have seen, is the nature of scarcity giving rise to potential for conflict which
implies property rights. To demonstrate the failure of this theory more thoroughly, allow
me to quote Kinsella at length. As noted before, some libertarian IP advocates, such
as Rand, hold that creation is the source of property rights. This confuses the nature
and reasons for property rights which lie in the undeniable fact of scarcity. Given scarcity
and the corresponding possibility of conflict in the use of resources, conflicts are avoided
and piecing cooperation are achieved by allocating property rights to such resources.
And the purpose of property rights dictates the nature of such rules. For if the rules
allocating property rights are to serve as objective rules that all can agree upon so
as to avoid conflict, they cannot be biased or arbitrary. For this reason, unknown resources
come to be owned, homesteaded or appropriated, by the first possessor. The general rule then
is that ownership of a given scarce resource can be identified by determining who first
occupied it. There are various ways to possess or occupy resources, and differing ways to
demonstrate or prove such occupation, depending on the nature of the resource and the use to
which it is put. Thus I can pluck an apple from the wild and thereby homestead it, or
I can fence in a plot of land for a farm. It is sometimes said that one form of occupation
is forming or creating the thing. For example, I can sculpt the statue from block of marble,
or forge a sword from raw metal, or even create a farm on a plot of land. We can see from
these examples that creation is relevant to the question of ownership of a given created
scarce resource such as a statue, sword or farm, only to the extent that the act of
creation is an act of occupation, or is otherwise evidence of first occupation. However, creation
itself does not justify ownership in things, it is neither necessary nor sufficient. One
cannot create some possibly disputed scarce resource without first using the raw materials
used to create the item. But these raw materials are scarce, and either I own them or I do not.
If not, then I do not own the resulting product. If I own the inputs, then by virtue of such
ownership, I own the resulting thing into which I transform them. Consider the forging of
a sword. If I own some raw metal, because I mined it from ground I owned, then I own
the same metal after I have shaped it into a sword. I do not need to rely on the fact
of creation to own the sword, but only on my ownership of the factors used to make the
sword. And I do not need creation to come to own the factors, since I can homestead them
simply by mining them from the ground and thereby becoming the first possessor. On the
other hand, if I fashion a sword using your metal, I do not own the resulting sword. In
fact, I may owe you damages for trespass or conversion.
Long's second case, where a man transfers title to his property to some group, fails on the
grounds that it does not resolve the contradiction, therefore making that contract invalid. Contract
theory will be elucidated thoroughly in a future lesson, so I will not explain this
point too deeply here. Just note that it will be seen that contract theory arises from
property theory, and therefore you cannot have contracts which allow for contradictory
property claims. Long is essentially putting the cart before the horse. A further potential
solution for group property rights is the polycentrist solution. To the polycentrist, law
in a libertarian society is decided by reference to competing arbitrators, these judges could
settle disputes, and thus determine the arrangement of property. So for our example of A through
Z all collectively on the stick, they would simply have to go to some judge to decide
who has just possession. The problem with this is that it is confused about the nature
of law, justice cannot be decreed by man, rather it depends on the normative structure
of argumentation. And second, the contradiction is still not resolved. If this judge rules
in favour of A, B did not own the stick, and vice versa. Companies are often forwarded as a
counter example to this thesis. It is said that multiple people can come together to own
shares in a given enterprise, and thus communally own said enterprise. This counter example
is confused about what a company is. Men do not go out into nature and find companies
which they then homestead, rather companies are specific relationships between men. They
are constructed via a web of contracts. Just as a person cannot own friendship or marriage,
they cannot own a firm, not legally at least. The specific property being directed by the
company must be owned by a single individual, perhaps the CEO or another such person. This
does not mean that the CEO can do whatever he wishes with his property. It may be the
case that there is a contract such that if he uses a property for purposes contrary to
the shareholders' voted upon goal, then the title of that property is transferred to some
other person who then becomes the CEO. Nowhere in such a conception is any property owned
by multiple people. There is a potential conundrum for this theory of homesteading, which goes
as follows. There are three sections of land, A, B and C, as pictured. Crusoe comes along
in homesteads A, Friday currently resides somewhere in C. Because Crusoe does not own
B, Friday does not have a duty towards Crusoe to not enter it. And because Crusoe does
own A, Friday does have a duty to Crusoe not to enter A. So Friday is allowed to enter
B, but not A. However, due to the donut shape of Crusoe's homestead, to enter B implies
entering A. Hence a contradiction arises, Friday both has a duty not to enter B and he
does not have said duty. That is to say, Crusoe is acting like he is the owner of B
when he is in fact not. This is called forestalling. The proposed solution put forth
by those in the Walter Block camp is the Blockean proviso. Essentially, they claim that the contradiction
arises from assuming that Crusoe has indeed homesteaded all of A. Therefore, to resolve
the contradiction, these donut homesteads must be disallowed. This formulation provided by
Åukasz Dominiak resolves a counter-argument made by Kinsella, where he imagines that the
donut is not owned by Crusoe himself, but by 100 Crusoes, we can call Crusoe 1 through
to Crusoe 100, which of these individual segments does Friday have the right to cross over,
and why not any of the others? Surely if they each sequentially homesteaded their individual
segments, none of them are individually forestalling. The solution to this is that it is Crusoe
100 who seals up the donut who has committed the crime, as he was not able to homestead
that final section. However, there is a way to resolve this contradiction without any
need for a proviso. As Kinsella writes in defence of embordering-as-homesteading, utilising
de Jasay's "let exclusion stand" principle. In a nutshell, de Jasay equates property with
its owners excluding others from using it, for example by fencing an immovable property,
e.g. land, or finding and creating and keeping movable property. Thus, the principle means
let ownership stand, e.g. that claims to ownership of property, appropriated from the state of
nature are acquired ultimately through a chain of titles tracing back to such an appropriation,
should be respected. daisie utilises this idea to demolish the criticism that homesteading
unowned resources unilaterally and unjustifiably imposes on others moral duties to refrain
from interfering. I.e. it is the very nature of property that the owner excludes others
from using it. We can then say that Crusoe in excluding others from this previously unowned
territory, B, thereby becomes its owner. It is this act of exclusion which is Crusoe initially
directing the use of both the donut and the donut-hole. This idea of "let exclusion stand"
sheds light also on the falsehood of the notion that property rights must be limited because
if they are not, I would be permitted to use my gun to shoot an innocent man. This
is false because my property right in that gun does not mean that I am allowed to use
that gun for whatever I want. It means that I have a right to exclude people from using
the gun for what they want. This isn't particularly surprising either. I would also not be permitted
to use a stolen gun to shoot someone. Who owns the gun being used for the shooting isn't
relevant to the question of whether the shooting is just or not. Kinsella goes on. Note that
the de Jasayan idea of let exclusion stand, or the Hoppean idea that the prior letter distinction
is of crucial importance, also sheds light on the nature of homesteading itself. Often
the question is asked, as to what types of acts constitute our sufficient for homesteading,
or in bordering its hopper sometimes refers to it. What type of labour must be mixed with
a thing, and to what property does the homesteading extend? What counts as sufficient homesteading,
etc. And we can see that in a way the answer to these questions is related to the issue
of what the thing is in dispute. In other words, if B claims ownership of a thing possessed
or formally possessed by A, then the very framing of this dispute helps to identify what the
thing is, and what counts as a possession of it. If B claims ownership of a given resource,
he must want the right to control it according to its nature. Then the question comes, did
someone else previously control it, according to its nature? I.e. did someone else already
homesteaded, so that B is only a latecomer. This ties in with day you say is a let exclusion
stand principle, which rests on the idea that if someone is actually able to control a resource,
such that others are excluded, then this exclusion should stand. Of course, the physical nature
of a given scarce resource, and the way in which humans use such resources, will determine
the nature of actions needed to control it and exclude others.
DSA, as a matter of fact, considers two basic types of appropriation, finding and keeping,
and enclosure. The former applies primarily to movable objects that may be found, taken
and hidden, or used exclusively. Since the thing has no prior owner, prima facia, no one
isn't entitled to object to first possess or claiming ownership. For immovable property,
land, possession is taken by enclosing the land, and incurring exclusion costs, e.g. erecting
importance. Again, similar to Hoppe's embroidering, establishing an objective, intersubjectively
as obtainable border. As, in the case with movables, others lost the opportunity to
appropriate the property, does not give rise to a claim sufficient to oust the first possessor.
If it did, it would be an ownership claim. So in the case where Friday is in C, Crusoe
instantly becomes the owner of both A and B, after he completes his embordering. In
the case where Friday is in B, assuming nobody else is in C, Crusoe would become the immediate
owner of both A and C. What about the case where there are people or homesteaded
property in both B and C? In that situation, it becomes clear that Crusoe would indeed
be forestalling in fencing off A, as he could not become the owner of owned property on either
side of his border. That is to say, this type of fencing off would be claiming possession,
not of unowned land, but of the owned property of others.
I have come to recognise a slight terminological problem regarding the definition of ownership.
Initially for this course, I defined ownership as just possession, that is to say that A owns
alpha if A can justify his possession of alpha. This terminology strikes him as being entirely
reasonable on its face, and for some purposes, such as the discussion of homesteading above,
it works perfectly fine. However, there are some issues with using just possession as
your definition of ownership. First, how does one apply this terminology to situations
where there is no conflict, and yet the owner of a thing is not in possession of it? Consider
inviting your friend over to watch some TV. Your friend sits on your sofa, and thus he is engaged
in some partial possession of the sofa, and of the sitting room. Given there is no conflict,
could you ask your friend to leave if you no longer want him to sit there? Well, he was
able to justify his possession of the sitting room, so did he not therefore own it? And
if he owns it, what right have you to tell him to leave?
This issue could be solved through some notion of antecedent vs descendant property rights,
i.e. your property rights in the sofa, and the sitting room are antecedent to your friends
right, and the antecedent right must prevail in a given conflict. I have no particular
issue with others using this terminology, but it would make the wording of the above proof
that ownership is exclusive a little bit tedious for my liking. As such in this course,
I shall use the terminology that ownership is just direction, which is analogous to
de Jasay's idea that ownership of a thing involves controlling it, and is also
reminiscent of the Misesian idea of socialism being a society wherein a single will directs
the factors of production. Furthermore, defining ownership in terms of who has the right to
control or direct a given property will be useful in later lessons when describing the
right to retribute and the right of guardianship as property rights. These things are scarce
so our property theory has to cover them, but they aren't physical, so its odd to
describe them in terms of possession. This course would be incomplete without at least
a brief treatment of so-called intellectual property rights, though this section will
indeed be brief as I already have an extensive video going over the topic. All that will
be covered here is a proof that intellectual property rights are impossible, and are rather
monopoly grants, and a brief demonstration that said intellectual monopoly grants are
per se criminal. First, to demonstrate that intellectual property rights are strictly
impossible, we consider the nature of property. To say that a person A has a property right
in X is to say that A should win any conflict over the use of X. Briefly, a conflict is
defined as contradictory actions, so if Crusoe is using a stick to spearfish and Friday comes
along and tries to use that same stick to stoke his fire, we have a conflict. The two
actions cannot take place simultaneously. One action excludes the other. Here we see
that having a property right in X is necessarily exclusionary. We say that something is scarce
if when you use it you exclude other people from being able to use it at the same time.
The issue with so-called intellectual property is that ideas are not scarce, so you can't
have a property right in an idea. If Crusoe finds a stick in nature and figures out how
to use it to fish, his use of the stick excludes Friday, but his use of the idea of spearfishing
does not exclude Friday. Friday is fully capable of finding a different stick and using it
to spearfish at the exact same time. We notice that Friday has to find a different stick,
but he does not have to find a different idea. One person having an idea excludes nobody
else from having that same idea at the same time, so conflicts over ideas are simply impossible.
Therefore, if Crusoe were to exclude other people from using his idea of spearfishing,
he is not doing so in defence of a property right. Instead, he is criminally threatening
and/or attacking people who want to use their own property to spearfish. If a man comes
up with a new mouse trap design and patents it, then claims to everyone else that they are
no longer allowed to use that same design, he is indirectly threatening them with violence
through the use of the state. Intellectual property therefore constitutes a criminal threat,
and crime is something to be opposed. Furthermore, to adopt a consistent intellectual property
ethic is to accept ethical stasis. The IP ethic could be stated that any late-comer to
an idea must first ask the first-comer to that idea permission before they may use it.
But anyone who is not the first guy who thought of the idea of asking someone else's permission
in order to use their idea must ask his permission in order to ask someone else's permission.
But they must first ask his permission to ask his permission, and so on, ad infinitum.
The IP ethic then implies the near-immediate cessation of all action, and therefore implies
the death of humanity, so it cannot possibly make for a human ethic.