1. The nature of law
If ethics is a normative discipline that identifies and classifies certain sets of actions as
good or evil, right or wrong, then tort or criminal law is a subset of ethics, identifying
certain actions as appropriate for the use of violence against them. The law says that
action X should be illegal and therefore should be combated by the violence of the law. The
law is a set of ought or normative propositions.
Marry Rothbard
To proceed with an explication of Austrian legal theory, we must first understand what
the nature of law is. First, law is a normative standard. That is to say, law is evaluative.
Legal theory identifies a group of criminals and a group of non-criminals, with reference
to a norm. However, there are normative standards that law does not cover, such as the question
of where to plant one's crops or by what standard art should be judged. That is to say, there
may be certain norms, certain guides to action, which are not covered by law. So law cannot
be exhaustive of evaluative philosophy. Second, we know that law deals with justice. That
is to say, law prohibits that which is unjust and permits that which is just. What is meant
by saying that X is just is that X can be argumentatively justified. So law is a normative
standard which guides men to just over unjust actions.
Third, argumentative justification is a human action, requiring the use of scarce means.
Action is defined as purposeful behaviour. It is the implementation of some scarce means
towards some end. Consider the example of John eating a ham sandwich to satiate his
hunger. His end is the removal of the hunger, and his means to achieve this end is the ham
sandwich. Of note here is that the means a man employs is necessarily scarce, which means
that his use of it prevents others from being able to use it. Therefore, in argumentatively
justifying anything, a man has to concern himself with scarcity. Fourth, because of scarcity,
there is a possibility for conflicts. Conflicts are defined as contradictory actions. So if
Crusoe and Friday are on an island, and Crusoe is trying to use a stick to spearfish at the
same time that Friday is trying to use it to stoke his fire, we have a conflict. The
stick is scarce, so it's use by one man, prevents the other man from using it. So only
one action, spearfishing or stoking of the fire, is able to take place. That is to say
that one action excludes the other. Fifth, because the possibility for conflicts exists
and cannot be ignored in argumentative justification, any legal theory must assign exclusive property
rights so as to determine the just winner in a given conflict. That is to say, law identifies
which sets of people are engaged in just direction, non-criminals, and which are engaged in unjust
direction, criminals. In other words, law couldn't assign that a given direction of
some means is both just and unjust. Here, a property right in alpha, held by A, means
that A is the one who has the right to direct the use of alpha.
Sixth, a position on the just winner in a conflict which is to say a position on law
is a position on ethics. Ethics is the area of philosophy which deals in general with
guides to man's action, i.e. what man ought do. Specifically, law is a subset of ethics which
deals with who should have possession of what, or more specifically, who should be the one
directing the possession of what. We can therefore define law as ethics applied to the issue
of conflicts. This is specifically a subset of interpersonal ethics, contrasted with autistic
ethics which deals with how the man alone should act. So ethics is made up of autistic
and interpersonal ethics, and law is a subset of the latter, dealing not in general with
how men should interact, but with that subset of interactions which are defined as conflicts.
Consider what it would mean to say that law is not in fact a subset of ethics. A claims
that he cannot justify his direction of the use of alpha, but also said that he should
nevertheless be its director. What is meant by A claiming that he should direct alpha?
This claim by A is in attempt to justify A's direction, which A claims that he cannot
do, therefore A is in contradiction. We shall see shortly that contradictions are
falsehoods, therefore meaning that it cannot be the case that A should be the director where
said direction is unjust. So law must be a subset of ethics. There does not exist any
legal claim, which is not also a moral claim. As we have seen, law is strictly derivable
from the nature of argumentation as a human action, employing scarce physical means, therefore
to assert that there are multiple different legal codes is to assert that there are multiple
different logics, which is called polylogism. Legal polylogism then is the claim that different
men may be able to adopt different logics in their argumentative justification of a system
of property rights. The general problem with legal polylogism is that implies contradiction.
Because for there to be different legal codes, A through Z, A must be incompatible with every
other legal code, B through Z, in at least one aspect, or else they would not be different,
but the same, and we would be back to singular law. Imagine that A and B are incompatible
on action alpha. A claims it to be just, and B claims it to be unjust. The legal polylogist
asserts that both A and B are correct. That alpha can both be justified, and it cannot
be justified. A contradiction. The problem here is that contradictions are false, which
we can see from the nature of argumentation. Imagine Sally and Eric are in an argument
over the truth of the proposition P. Eric claims that P is the case, and Sally claims
that P is not the case. This means that Eric asserts P, and Sally asserts the negation
of P. For Sally's case to be considered an attempted refutation of Eric, rather than
simply speaking gibberish or telling a joke, she must presuppose that P and not P cannot
both be correct. That is to say, in disputing anything, you presuppose the law of non-contradiction.
The Stanford Encyclopædia of Philosophy defines legal positivism as the thesis that the existence
and content of law depends on social facts and not on its merits. In other words, a legal
positivist claims that law is not a subset of ethics, and thus there could potentially
be such a thing as a virtuous crime to a legal positivist. The article elaborates. The positivist
thesis does not say that laws merits are unintelligible, unimportant, or peripheral to the
philosophy of law. It says that they do not determine whether laws or legal systems exist.
Whether a society has a legal system depends on the presence of certain structures of governance,
not on the extent to which it satisfies ideals of justice, democracy, or rule of law. What
laws are enforced in that system depends on what social standards as officials recognise
as authoritative. For example, legislative enactments, judicial decisions, or social
customs. The fact that a policy would be just, wise, efficient, or prudent is near a sufficient
reason to thinking that it is actually the law, and the fact that it is unjust, unwise,
inefficient, or imprudent, is never sufficient reason for doubting it. According to positivism,
law is a matter of what has been posited, ordered, decided, practised, tolerated, etc.
Law to the legal positivist then is a description of the specific arrangement of possessions
that actually obtain, rather than a theory describing the just arrangement of possessions.
Let's break that down. The legal positivist is making the claim that law has nothing
to do with justice. Rather, the law is determined by raw might. That is, if A is able to physically
defeat B in a conflict, and thus perform an action alpha, the positivist goes only as
far as to point and say, look, A won the conflict. Therefore, the law on this conflict
is that A won, but this is a complete non-theory. Okay, A won, so what? How on earth they think
they get to cordon off an area of philosophy and take the label law for what can be summed
up in the sentence, whoever wins a given conflict has won that conflict, is beyond me. The legal
positivist as such can't even elucidate a theory predicting when people will choose
to engage in a conflict and who is likely to win. Those would be the domains of economics
and military theory, respectively. The problems with positivist thesis do not stop here. Even
if a positivist were to reject the separation of law and justice, claiming that might makes
right, their theory is still in ruin, because the might-makes-right theory of law is a form
of legal polylogism. It is the claim that the logic of which actions are justifiable can
change depending on whether you are able to successfully carry out that action and muscle
away anybody who gets in the way. As we saw above, legal polylogism in general is false,
therefore this form of legal positivism is false also. Any notion of a source of rights is
indicative of positivism, and more fundamentally of the fallacy of primacy of consciousness.
Rights simply are, they don't come from some consciousness, whether divine or social
or individual. It is not arbitrary thoughts or decrees which are the source of rights,
but the logic of justification and conflict. So we have seen that the nature of law implies
that there must be a universal law. That is, any form of legal polylogism is necessarily
false. And further, to argue or dispute anything would be to presuppose the existence of a single
universal law. We can say that this universal law is therefore true law, as it is the normative
foundation of argumentation and argumentation is a practical precondition for ascertaining
the truth or validity of anything. Imagine attempting to dispute that this law is true.
First you would have to accept its validity, as that validity is implied by the act of
argumentation, so you would therefore be explicitly proclaiming it to be false, whilst implicitly
presupposing it to be true, which is a contradiction. A contradiction not between propositions,
but between a proposition and the very act of proposing it. But there is no such thing
as a free-floating proposition which does not come from an actor proposing it. Therefore,
there is an objective, natural law. It is this natural law which will be elucidated
in this course. We understand that its nature is that it is specifically a study of human
action. The general science of human action is called praxeology, so law is a sub-science
of praxeology. Thus, it will be of use to briefly go over some basic praxeology here
to make comprehension of the rest of this course easier. First, human action is purposeful
behaviour. It is distinct from mere behaviour in that the former involves some intentional
aiming at a goal, where the latter does not. So the operation of a man's digestive system
or the beating of his heart can be understood as mere mechanistic behaviour, as the man does
not intend to digest or beat his heart. And on the other hand, his choosing to eat food
or shock himself with a defibrillator are purposeful, so these are not mere behaviours,
but are rather actions. It is this notion of choice which is crucial to understanding
something as an action. Action involves a deliberate attempt to change the world to one
that man finds more preferable to the alternative where he does not engage in said action. It
is this choice of what man prefers over the alternative, that is the characteristic mark
of action. Therefore, for an action to be possible in the first place, (1) a man must
experience some state of uneasiness, something that he doesn't like, (2) he must imagine
a state of the world without this uneasiness, and (3) he must believe that a given action
will work to achieve this imagined state without the uneasiness. When a man acts, the result
he wishes to achieve can be called his end. Man always acts to remove uneasiness, and
his end is the imagined state without said uneasiness. For man to achieve the end desired,
he must employ certain means. A metaphysical entity is understood as a means when a human
plans to employ, or is employing it for the attainment of some end. As has been shown,
for a man to engage in an action X as opposed to not X, implies that the man prefers to engage
in action X as opposed to not X. What this preference means is that the man thinks he
should do X, rather the alternative for whatever reason.
In the context of legal analysis, one important praxeological doctrine is the distinction between
action and mere behaviour. The difference between action and behaviour boils down to intent.
Action is an individual's intentional intervention in the physical world, via certain selected
means, with the purpose of attaining a state of affairs that is preferable to the conditions
that would prevail in the absence of the action.
Mere behaviour, by contrast, is a person's physical movements that are not undertaken
intentionally and that do not manifest any purpose, plan, or design. In learning philosophy
it is often of great use of the student to study the history of philosophy, such that an understanding
of what ideas have been had and where they came from can be attained. Thus, a brief overview
of the history of (legal) philosophy seems appropriate to include here.
Kinsella provides such a brief overview. In modern times, the two dominant legal systems
are the common law and the civil law, based on the body of English case law that developed
gradually over the centuries. The common law spread to English colonies in commonwealths
like America, Canada, and Australia. Modern civil law systems are based on Roman law,
which, like the common law, developed many of its important legal principles in the
accumulated decisions of jurists in thousands of cases. Virtually all of Europe and many
other jurisdictions, including Louisiana, Puerto Rico, and Quebec, a civil law system.
In the common law and Roman law, they're eventually evolved very sophisticated bodies
of legal principles, concepts, methodology, and precedence. Because the classical common
law and Roman law develop the large bulk of their legal principles through the decision
and discussion of cases, they serve as rough examples of decentralized systems of a judge
found law, and as do largely private customary law systems like the law merchant. So broadly
speaking, there are two types of legal systems; (1) those based on "judge-found" law, and
(2) those where the legal principles are decreed by legislation. Roman law and English common
law are examples of the former, where the legal principles are obtained by judges attempting
to do justice in a number of individual cases, which is why such systems are described as
case law systems. Modern civil law, on the other hand, is the prime example of a legislated
system, where principles are embodied in a "Civil Code" derived from the arbitrary decree
of the legislative branch. Under a legislative system, the judges are not attempting to do
justice in some particular dispute, rather they make reference to the legislative fiat
on this matter. So appealing to a judge that the given law is unjust is not going to work
where it would in a case law system. The distinction between judge found law and law as decreed
by legislative fiat is an important one. In a decentralized case law system, the judges
are at least setting out to do justice. This is in stark distinction to a fiat law system,
where the so-called laws are not rational, but rather arbitrary commandments issued top
down by the legislature. Because these commandments are arbitrary, there is nothing objective
about the laws in such a system. And because the laws are non-objective, but rather based
an arbitrary subjective whim, such a system is per se incompatible with justice and freedom.
Even statutes that seem to embody libertarian principles simultaneously subvert those principles.
Because in such a legislative system, a victim of an objective crime cannot appeal to the
objective principles of justice, judges can only accidentally make the right call, and
they have no way of determining the correct compensation for the victim. In fact, most
often compensating the victim is completely ignored. Instead, the state will charge the
victim money in the form of taxes to punish the criminal by some one-size-fits-all punishment
scheme, usually imprisonment. Bruno Leoni has pointed out further that fiat law systems
will tend towards more legal uncertainty. This is because where law is determined by
arbitrary fiat, rather than objective principles of justice, it can change at any moment. This
has the effect of making it challenging to even begin to follow the law in the first
place. Consider the many thousands of pages of legislation that are committed to the
books. Professional lawyers whose job is to know the law could not hope to keep up with
this, let alone random citizens. There's also no means of preventing contradictions
from occurring between statutes, potentially making it literally impossible to follow the
law, even if you know about every word of it. This is not so with a found law system,
where there has to be coherence between different objective principles. And of course, if it's
impossible to follow the law, then law cannot guide men's actions. So impossible fiat law
is not law at all. To sum up, the job of the rational jurist is to explicate, discover
objective standards of law. The role of the judge is to attempt to apply this objective
body of law in a given case. The rational judge attempts to do justice, rather than apply
or create, i.e. posit, arbitrary rules based on whim. This is an important insight,
those in the David Friedman camp, called polycentrists, view an anarcho-capitalist legal
order as one of multi-legislation, multi-centralized law, rather than decentralized judge found
law. The free market judge is not a mini-legislator, coming up with arbitrary decrees. He is and
must be attempting to apply objective legal principles. We can, from the armchair, explicate
such an objective body of law. What we cannot do is actually elaborate every possible case
that might come up. This is the role of the judge, to attempt to apply abstract and objective
principles to concrete cases.